好的，你们能听到我说话吗？
Alright, can you guys hear me?
是的。
Yes.
谢谢。
Thank you.
好的，今天我主要想说的是微内核，
Alright, today I want to talk about talk mostly about micro kernels,
首先，我们来了解一些背景，
but first a little bit of context
以帮助解释
to sort of help explain
为什么人们一开始会探索微内核，
why people explored micro kernels in the first place,
人们获得微内核，
this people got the micro kernels
试着广泛地思考内核应该做什么，
by trying to think about more broadly about what kernels should actually do,
就像我们在 xv6 中，
like we've you know with xv6,
某种程度上，做 Unix 所做的事情，
is sort of does the things that Unix does
我们采用了这组抽象概念和系统调用，
and we kind of take that set of abstractions and system calls
并保留了内核中的设施，
and keep sort of facilities inside the kernels,
理所当然是我们试图设计的目标，
kind of for granted is the target of what we're trying to design,
但是完全值得怀疑，
but it's totally worth wondering,
天哪，内核首先应该做什么，
gosh, what should a kernel do in the first place,
也许是 xv6 或 Linux 所做的特定类型的事情，
maybe maybe the particular kind of stuff that xv6 or Linux does,
这不是最好的答案，
it's not really the best answer,
或者它是。
or maybe it is.
当然，我们这里的处境有些危险，
And of course we're on somewhat treacherous ground here,
因为现在我们，
because now we're we're,
内核是一种为程序员的开发平台，
what kernels are is kind of a development platform for programmers,
正如我们所知，
as we know,
程序员，不同的人有非常不同的主观偏好，
programmers different people have very different sort of subjective preferences
他们喜欢在什么样的基础设施上编程。
about what kind of infrastructure they like to program on.
所以我们不一定要期待一个最好的答案，
So we can't necessarily expect a single best answer,
但是我们可以期望学到一些东西，
but we can expect to maybe learn something,
或许可以取得一些进展，
and maybe make some progress
通过努力想一想可能的答案。
by trying to think about what answers might be.
所以首先，
So first of all,
让我试着明确传统的方法，
let me try to crystallize what the traditional approaches
我们应该使用什么样的内核接口，
to what kind of kernel interfaces we ought to be using
Linux ， Unix 和 xv6 都是例子，
and Linux and Unix and xv6 are all examples of,
我个人所说的传统设计方法的例子，
of what I personally call a traditional design approach,
但是用另一个词来形容它，
but another word for it,
那是一种概括，
that kind of summarizes,
这种方法最终像是宏大而单一的。
but this approach has ended up like is monolithic.
宏大而单一的。
Monolithic.
这意味着内核是一个单一的大程序，
And what that means is that the kernel is a single big program,
它可以做各种各样的事情，
that does all kinds of things,
都在同一个程序内。
all within the same program.
事实上，这确实反映了
And indeed this really reflects
人们对内核应该做什么的想法，
the way people thought about what kernels ought to be doing
像 Linux 这样的内核的一个特点是，
a real hallmark of kernels like Linux is
它们提供了强大的抽象，
that they have, they provide powerful abstractions,
他们选择像文件系统这样的东西，
you know they choose things like file systems
这是一个复杂的项目，
and which is really a complicated item,
它们提供文件系统，
and they present file systems
文件、目录和文件描述符作为它们的接口，
and files and directories and file descriptors as their interface,
而不是将磁盘硬件作为它们与应用程序的接口，
rather than for example presenting disk hardware as their interface to applications,
所以，使用强大的抽象，
so, and using presenting powerful abstractions
而不是非常低级别的抽象有一些很大的优势，
instead of very low-level abstractions has some big advantages,
宏内核通常有一种很大的抽象，
monolithic kernels often have a sort of big abstractions,
比如，文件系统。
like, file, the file system.
大的抽象的一个优点是
One advantage of big abstract is
它们通常是可移植的文件和目录，
that they're often portable of files and directories,
你可以在所有类型的存储上实现文件和目录，
you can implement files and directories on all kinds of storage
你可以使用文件和目录，
and file you can use files and directories,
而不必担心运行的磁盘的品牌，
[] having to worry about what brand of disk drive is running on
或者它可能是固态硬盘而不是硬盘，
or maybe it's an ssd instead of a hard drive,
或者它可能是一个网络文件系统，
or maybe it's a network file system
所有的接口都是一样的，
and all its the same interface,
因为文件系统接口非常抽象。
because the file system interface is pretty high level pretty abstract.
所以，这样做的一个好处是，
So, an advantage of this is
获得可移植性的方法，
that the way to get portability,
编写应用程序并使其在各种不同的硬件上运行，
write an application and have it run on all kinds of different hardware
而不必修改应用程序。
without having to modify the application.
另一个例子是，
Another example of this is that
Unix Linux 提供了地址空间抽象。
Unix Linux provides an address space abstraction
而不是提供一些东西，
rather than providing something that's likes,
而不是提供对 MMU 硬件的直接访问，
rather than providing direct access to the MMU hardware
对于可移植性有用，
and that's useful for portability
并且对应用程序隐藏了复杂性。
and sort of hide complexity from applications.
所以，这些强大的抽象的另一大优势，
So another big advantage of these powerful abstractions,
它们往往对应用程序隐藏了复杂性。
they tend to hide complexity from applications.
比如 xv6 提供的文件描述符接口，
The, so for example the file descriptor interface that xv6 provides,
它是非常简单的接口，
it's very simple interface,
但你只需要读写文件描述符，
but you just read and write on file descriptors,
再简单不过了，
couldn't get much simpler,
但是在它的背后是非常复杂的代码，
but behind it is very complicated code
对于读写磁盘上的文件系统。
for actually reading and writing a disk, the file system on disk.
这对程序员来说是件好事，
And that's nice for programmers,
但它会让内核变得很大很复杂，
but it makes for a big complex kernel,
这些大的抽象还帮助内核管理和共享资源，
these big abstractions also help the kernel manage and share resources,
我们已经委托给内核的事情，比如内存管理，
we've delegated to the kernel things, like memory management,
内核跟踪哪些内存是空闲的，
the kernel keeps track of what memories free,
类似地，内核跟踪磁盘的哪些部分是空闲的，
we similarly the kernel keeps track of what parts of the disk are free,
当前磁盘的哪些部分在使用。
in what parts of the disk current current use.
所以程序员们不用考虑它，
So programmers don't get to think about it,
再一次，它简化了程序，
and that again, it simplifies programs,
它甚至还有助于增强健壮性和安全性，
it also helps with robustness and security even,
因为如果允许程序决定磁盘的哪些部分是空闲的，
because if programs are allowed to decide what parts of the disk are free or not,
那么也许一个程序可以使用
then maybe one program could use
另一个程序已经在使用的磁盘的一部分。
a part of the disk that's already being used by another program.
所以实际上，内核负责资源管理，
So the fact that the kernel is in charge of resource management,
帮助共享并帮助确保安全，
helps with sharing and helps with security,
但这也是某种程度上导致内核变大。
but again it's a force that sort of causes the kernel to be big.
所以不管怎样，
So anyway,
让内核负责所有这些有趣的抽象，
so having the kernel being charge of all these sort of juicy abstractions,
即使它们只有简单的接口，
that even if they have simple interfaces,
里面有很多复杂的东西，
have a lot of complexity inside,
让内核变成又大又复杂的东西。
have let kernels to be big and complex items.
而这种整体式设计的另一个方面是，
And another aspect of this monolithic design approaches,
因为这都是一个程序，
that because it's all one program,
所有不同的内核子系统，
all the different kernel subsystems,
比如文件系统，内存分配器，调度器以及虚拟内存，
like the file system and the memory allocator and scheduler and virtual memories,
它们都是一个大的程序的一部分，
they're all part of one big integrated program,
这意味着它们可以窥探彼此的数据结构，
it means that they can peer into each others data structures,
所以，这往往会使设施的实施变得更容易，
and so that's just tended to make it much easier to implement facilities,
它在某种程度上是不止一个的一部分，
that are sort of parts of more than one
或者你认为不止一种类型的模块或子系统，
or what you might think of as more than one kind of module or subsystem,
比如，像 exec 这样的系统调用，
so for example a system call like exec,
exec 深入文件系统，
exec has its fingers deeply into file system,
因为它读取磁盘的二进制映像，
because it's reading binary images of the disk
以加载内存，
in order to load the memory,
它还深入到内存分配和虚拟内存分页系统，
it also has its fingers into the memory allocation and virtual memory paging system,
因为它需要设置新进程的地址空间，
because it needs to set up the address space of the new process,
但这真的很容易，
but it's really easy,
在 xv6 或 Linux 中这样做没有问题，
there's no problem with doing that in xv6 or Linux,
因为文件系统都在那里，
because both all the file system is right there,
在同一个内核程序中，
in the same kernel program
虚拟内存系统也是同一程序的一部分，
and the virtual memory system is also right there as part of the same program
如果你以某种方式严格分割，
and if you somehow there was a rigid split
在文件系统和虚拟内存系统之间，
between the file system and the virtual memory system,
要实现像 exec 这样的东西会困难得多，
would be much harder to implement something like exec,
它深入到这两个[]。
that has sort of fingers in both of these [].
但是在宏系统中，只有一个大程序，
But in a monolithic system just one big program,
就容易多了。
it's much easier.
另一件事情让实现软件
Another thing that makes implementing software
在 xv6 或 Linux 这样的宏内核中更简单的是，
inside a monolithic kernel like xv6 or Linux easy is that
所有代码都以完全硬件权限运行，
all the code runs with full hardware privileges,
比如，所有 xv6 都在管理员模式下运行，
all xv6 runs in supervisor mode for example,
这意味着没有限制，没有恼人，
which means there's no limits there's no irritating,
你不能写那段内存，
oh, you can't you know me to write that memory here,
因为你没有足够的权限，
because you don't have enough privilege,
所有内核代码都以某种最大权限运行，
all the kernel code runs with sort of maximum privilege,
像 Linux 这样的操作系统也是如此。
and you know the same is true of operating systems like Linux.
所以这个设计策略，
So, this design strategy,
对于内核开发者来说是非常方便的，
it's very convenient for kernel developers
它使得构建这些大型抽象变得很容易，
and it's made it easy to build these big abstractions
这对应用程序开发人员来说是方便的，
which are convenient for application developers,
然而，这里也有一些批评，
however, there's also a certain amount to criticize
对于传统的宏方法。
with the monolithic, traditional monolithic approach.
这是开始的动力之一，
And this is starting to be part of the motivation
来研究其他架构，比如微内核，
for looking at other architectures, like micro kernels,
所以你可能会问，
so you might ask,
为什么不是宏内核。
why not monolithic kernels.
其中之一就是它们又大又复杂，
So one is just that they're big and complex,
所以任何 Linux 系统都取决于你是如何计算的，
so anything that's Linux is depending on how you count,
Linux 在几十万到几百万行代码之间，
Linux somewhere between many hundreds of thousands and a few million lines of code
人们利用了这个事实，
and people really do take advantage of the fact,
Linux 的一部分可以查看其他部分的数据，
that one part of Linux can sort of look at the data of another
这使得编程变得更容易，
and that makes the programming easier,
但这也使得代码之间存在大量的互连和相互关系，
but it also makes there'd be a lot of interconnections and interrelationships between code
所以，它会是一个挑战，
and so it can be a bit challenging
有时查看 Linux 内核代码，
sometimes to look at the Linux kernel code
找出它的目的是什么，
and figure out what it's up to
任何时候，当你得到大程序，
and anytime you get big programs,
特别是那些复杂结构的程序，
especially ones that are a complex structure,
你会有 bug ，
you get bugs,
操作系统内核也不例外，
and operating system kernels are no exceptions
多年来，它们有各种各样的 bug ，
and over the years, they've had all kinds of bugs,
包括可用于安全目的的漏洞。
including bugs that are exploitable for security.
所以，这是一系列麻烦的关系，
So, so this is sort of trouble set of relationships,
如果你允许内核的大模型，
if you allow a big model of the kernel,
几乎可以肯定的是，
you almost certainly,
无法避免 bug 和可利用的安全问题，
can't avoid bugs and exploitable security problems
这是一个真正的问题。
and that's a real I mean there really is a problem.
人们对宏内核可能并不完全满意的另一个原因是，
Another reason why people are maybe not entirely happy with monolithic kernels is that,
随着时间的推移，它们往往只会增长，具有所有想要的功能，
they tend to just grow with all desirable features over time
所以 Linux 被用来做各种不同的事情，
and so you know Linux is used for all kinds of different things,
从电话听筒到桌面工作站，
from telephone handsets to a desktop workstations
从笔记本电脑，平板电脑到互联网上的服务器，
and laptops to tablets to servers on the Internet,
再到路由器，
to routers
这导致了 Linux ，
and that's caused Linux,
Linux 可以支持所有这些东西，这真是太棒了，
it's fantastic that Linux can support all those things,
但它使它变得非常笼统，
but it has caused it to be very general,
它支持很多不同的东西，
it has support in there for many many different things
任何应用程序，
and any one application
比如我运行 web 服务器，
like me running my web servers,
不需要比如 Linux 非常复杂的声卡支持，
unlikely to need for example Linux is very sophisticated sound card support,
所以这里有大量的东西，
so there's just a huge amount of stuff,
是为了让 Linux 成为通用的，
that's there for to allow Linux to be general purpose,
这很好，
which is good,
但也有一个担心，
but there's a worry,
一般用途往往意味着缓慢，
that general purpose is going to tend to mean slow,
可能对各种不同的东西都有好处，
that you know may be good for all kinds of different things,
但可能对任何特定的东西都不是最优的。
but maybe not optimum for anything in particular.
所以很难，
so it's very hard to,
当你试着做一些非常快的东西，
you know when you're trying to make something really fast,
最好让它只做一两件事，
it's great to have it just only do one or two things,
你可以专注于优化单个代码路径，
you can focus on optimizing a single code path,
但是如果你的软件需要做上千种不同的事情中的一个，
but if your software needs to do any one of a thousand different things,
专注优化要困难得多。
it's much harder to have focused optimization.
这就是， Linux 不一定很慢，
So this is, Linux is not necessarily slow,
但是，你可能会想，
but it's you know you might wonder,
它是否像可能的那样快，
if it's really as fast as it could possibly be
对于任何给定的情况。
for any given situation.
所以如果你仔细想想，
So if you think about it,
你如何考虑，
how do you think,
如果你考虑 Linux 或 xv6 中几乎所有东西，
if you think about almost anything in Linux or xv6,
你可能会想，它是否真的需要做它所做的每一件事，
you know you may wonder whether it really needs to do everything it does,
比如，如果你通过管道写入单个字节，
so, for example if you write a single byte over a pipe
从一个进程到另一个进程，
from one process to another,
但是有很多指令会被执行，
but there's a lot of instructions that get executed,
即使是 xv6 ，它是一个简单的内核，
even xv6 which is a simple kernel, right,
有缓冲，有锁，
there's buffering, you know there's locking,
有睡眠和唤醒，
there's could be a sleep and wakeup
在管道读写时，
during a pipe read and write,
可能有调度器，
there's maybe a scheduler
可能调用上下文切换，
in may called the scheduler context switch,
有很多东西可能不一定需要，
has a lot of stuff that's maybe not necessarily,
需要的绝对最小的，
the absolute minimum that would be required
将一个字节从一个进程移动到另一个进程。
to move a byte from one process to another.
这些大内核的另一个潜在问题是，
Another potential problem with these big kernels is that,
因为它们太大了，
they, because they're so big
而且它们故意去掉一些非常复杂的抽象，
and they sort of intentionally bite off some very sophisticated abstractions,
他们有很多设计决策，
they tend to have a lot of design decisions,
在内核中。
kind of baked into the kernel.
所以，在某些方面你不能，
So, you know in ways that you can't,
即使你不同意他们的观点，
even if you disagree with them,
你也不能，应用程序只能接受它。
you can't really you know [] applications just have to live with it.
所以，相反的，
So, you know as a as opposed to,
在某个幻想世界里，
in some fantasy world,
也许应用程序可以做出更多的决定，
maybe applications could make a lot more of the decisions,
所以有一些例子，
so you know some examples of things where
你可能会对 API 的设计方式感到失望，
you may just you may be bummed out by the way the API designed,
比如，在 Unix 中，
for example in a Unix,
你可以等待自己的子进程，
you can wait for a process your own children,
如果你 fork ，可以等待你的子进程，
if you fork, you can wait for your children,
但你不能等待其他进程，
but you can't wait for some other process
也许你想等待一个孙子进程或一个无关的进程，
and maybe you want to wait for a grandchild or an unrelated process,
但这不是一个选择，
but that's just not an option,
它不是这样工作的，
it's just not the way things work,
即使这对你来说很方便，
even if it would be convenient for you,
也许您想要更改另一个进程地址空间的设置方式，
maybe you want to change the way another processes address space is set up,
也许可以调用和映射
you know maybe call and map on
你控制的另一个进程，
[] of another process that you're controlling,
但是，这也不是一个选择，
but again, that's just not an option,
你可以映射修改自己的地址空间，
you can map change your own address space,
但不能修改其他进程的地址空间，
but not changes other process address space,
可能是数据库，并且磁盘上有 B 树索引，
maybe a database and you have B-tree indexes on the disk
你可能知道很多关于在磁盘上布局 B 树的最快方法，
and you may know a lot about it the fastest way to layout B-tree on a disk,
但是如果你使用文件系统读写文件，
but if you're reading and writing files with the file system,
文件系统不知道你是在写入 B 树，
the file system has no idea that you're actually writing a B-tree
也不知道应该如何在磁盘上布局 B 树以实现最快的访问。
or how a B-tree ought to be laid out on a disk for fastest access.
所以如果你的数据库有点麻烦，
And so if your database you're going to be kind of bummed,
也许你很高兴有这个文件系统供你支配，
you know maybe you're happy that you have this file system at your disposal,
但它并没有真正做你想做的事。
but it doesn't really do what you want to do.
这就是设计决策到大内核中的感觉。
That's the sense in which a design decisions are often baked into big kernels.
最后，还有一种特殊的问题，
And finally, a specific sort of issue that,
所以它可能是在 20 世纪 90 年代出现的，
so it came up in a big way in the 1990s probably,
一种可扩展性的概念，
a notion of extensibility,
让程序能够在运行时修改内核，
that it might be desirable for programs to be able to change the kernel on the fly,
能够下载内核中的新代码，
to be able to download new code in the kernel
或者改变它的运作方式之类的，
or change the way it operates or something,
为了能让数据库
in order to do things like have databases
能够控制磁盘上的数据布局。
able to control the layout of data on the disk.
至少在过去的几十年里，
At least in decades past,
宏内核没有任何特定的功能，
monolithic kernels tended not to, to have any particular features,
来帮助这种扩展能力，
that help with this kind of extensive ability,
你只是困在内核中。
you're just stuck with whatever the kernel did.
好的。
Okay.
所以，这些都是人们考虑的一些问题，
So, these were sort of problems in the back of people's minds,
让他们思考其他的，
that let them to think about other kinds of,
操作系统设计其他体系结构的方式，
other ways of designing other architectures for operating systems
而且有很多想法，
and and there were a number of, a number of ideas,
有些与人们追求的截然不同，
some quite radically different that people pursued,
我们要谈的是其中一个，
we're going to talk about one of them,
今天特别受欢迎的一个，
particularly popular one today
这就是微内核的想法。
and that's the idea of micro kernels.
微内核，很多想法，
Micro kernels, although many of the ideas
或者回到计算机历史的开始，
or go back to the beginning of computer history,
它们变成一种热门的研究课题，
they became a sort of hot research topic,
可能从 20 世纪 80 年代中后期开始。
starting in maybe the mid to late 1980s.
最重要的想法是，
And the big idea,
顺便说一下，微内核这个词
so micro kernel this this word, by the way
指的是一种一般的方法，一个概念，
refers to a sort of general approach, a concept,
它不是任何特定的东西，
it doesn't refer to any specific artifact,
有许多人设计和构建操作系统，
there were many people who designed and built operating systems
根据微内核的一般方案，
that followed the general sort of plan for micro kernels,
但是，这些项目中的每一个，
but you know each of these projects,
最终设计和操作系统都可能有很大的不同。
ended up designing and operating systems may be quite different from the others.
所以关键的想法是微小的内核，
So the key idea was the tiny kernel,
仅支持 IPC 进程间通信，
that supported just IPC or inter process communication,
以及某种线程或任务的概念。
and some sort of notion of a threads or tasks.
所以，你有一个内核，它为你提供
So you have a kernel that provides you
一种类似于抽象的进程的概念，
a notion of sort of process like abstraction
进程之间可以互相通信，
and away for processes to communicate with each other,
通过这种进程间通信，
with this inter process communication
没有其他的了。
and nothing else.
其他你可能想做的事，
And everything else you might want to do,
比如要实现的文件系统，
like a file system you'd implement,
作为进程或任务在用户级代码，
as a process as a task as a user level code,
而不是在内核中。
not in the kernel at all.
所以，这里的图，
So picture for that,
现在我们使用 u 表示微内核，
maybe now we're going to use u for micro kernel,
微内核在下面这里，
and the micro kernel down here
在上面有用户空间进程，
and we got user space processes up here
我们可能会运行所有常见的进程，
and we might have all the kind of usual processes run,
也许要运行 vi ，我最喜欢的文本编辑器，
maybe we're gonna run vi, my favorite text editor,
还有我的编译器，我的窗口系统。
and my my compiler, my windows system.
但这里也像常用进程一样，
But also up here as usual processes,
我们使用文件系统，
we're going to have the file system,
就像用户空间中的服务器进程一样，
just as a server process in user space,
也许我们会有一个磁盘驱动程序，
maybe we're going to have a disk driver,
它们知道如何与我的磁盘硬件通信，
they know how to talk to my disk hardware,
也许我们有一个网络堆栈，
maybe we have a network stack,
它知道如何使用 TCP 与我的网卡交互，
that knows how to talk talk TCP to my network interface card,
也许我们有一个用户级别的进程，
maybe we'll have a user level process,
负责执行花哨的分页技巧，
that's in charge of doing fancy paging tricks,
比如内存映射文件，
like memory mapped files
或者可能实现写入时复制， fork 等东西。
or maybe implements copy-on-write fork or something.
当我的文本编辑器需要读取文件时，
And when my text editor needs to read a file,
它需要与文件系统交互，
it needs to talk the file system,
所以，它通过 IPC 进程间通信发送一条消息，
and so it's gonna send a a message via IPC inter process communication,
到文件系统服务器，
to the file system server,
其中包含所有文件系统代码，
which has all the file system code,
它是关于文件和目录，
it's about files and directories
并且文件系统服务器代码可能需要与磁盘交互，
and file system server code may need to talk to the disk,
所以它可能发送磁盘读取或写入，
so it might send another sort of disk read or write,
另一个 IPC ，
so another IPC to,
磁盘驱动以某种方式与硬件交互，
the disk driver which somehow talks this hardware,
这个驱动程序可能返回一个磁盘块到文件服务器，
this driver may return you know a disk block to the file server
在它完成它的事情之后，
after it does its thing,
也许文件服务器最终再次返回你请求的数据，
maybe the file server finally returns the data you ask for again
通过进程间通信消息，
by inter process communication messages,
回到我的文本编辑器。
back to my text editor.
但是这里需要注意的关键是，
But you know the the critical thing to notice here is that
内核中唯一要做的就是，
the only stuff going down here in the kernel is
支持这些进程、任务或线程，
support for these processes or tasks or threads,
无论它们是什么，
whatever they might be
支持进程间通信消息传递，没有其他的，
and support for the inter process communication message passing and nothing else,
下面没有文件系统，
there's no file system down here,
下面的内核中也没有设备驱动程序，
there's no device drivers necessarily down here in the kernel,
这里没有网络堆栈，
there's no network stack,
所有这些东西都在上面，
all that stuff is up here,
或多或少都是普通的用户级进程。
as more or less ordinary user level processes.
所以，它们会带来一个非常小的内核，
So they lead you to a very small kernel
包含相对较少的代码可以优化，
with a relatively little code optimize,
比如你可以优化 IPC ，
like you can optimize IPC
没有太多其他的事情要做。
and there's not much else going on.
所以这是我们要在剩下的这节课上讨论的图片，
And so this is the kind of picture we're going to talk about for the rest of the lecture
让你们了解这件事的最终的情况。
and just give you a taste of where this ended up.
实际上，今天仍在使用一种微内核，
There are actually still a micro kernels in use today,
事实上， L4 微内核，
and indeed the L4 micro kernel
是今天论文讨论的主题所使用的，
which is the topic of today's paper turns out to be used,
有很多 L4 实例运行，
there's many instances many many instances of L4 running,
因为它被用在很多手机里，
because it's used in a lot of cellphones
在小型控制器上控制手机无线电，
in the little micro controllers that control the cell phone radios
而且它也被用于最近的 iPhone ，
and it's also apparently used in recent iPhones
作为 iPhone 上的专用 enclave 处理器上运行的操作系统，
as the operating system that runs on a special dedicated enclave processor in the iPhone,
用于隐藏秘密的密钥。
that hides the secret cryptographic keys.
所以，有很多嵌入式，
So there's a bunch of embedded
微内核胜出
where these micro kernels have won out
在小型嵌入式专用计算机系统中，
in little embedded specialized computer systems,
不是笔记本，
not not laptops,
而是专用于单一专门任务的计算机，
but a computer dedicated to single specialized tasks
可能不需要 Linux 的复杂性，
where you may not need the complexity of Linux,
但是你确实需要一些操作系统。
but you do need some operating system.
另一件事，
And the other thing,
微内核的另一种最终结果是，
that's the other sort of final result from micro kernels is that,
用户级服务与其他程序通过 IPC 与它们交互，
the idea of user level services with with other programs talking to them with IPC,
也已经进入了很多操作系统，
that also has made its way into a lot of operating systems,
就像 Mac OS ，
like Mac OS,
它正运行着与你交谈，
which running right now to talk to you,
它既是一种普通的宏内核，
you know it's a sort of as well as being a kind of ordinary monolithic kernel,
它还很好地支持用户级服务，
it also has good support for a user level services
以及 Unix 进程之间与服务交互的 IPC ，
and IPC between Unix processes to talk to the service,
所以，那个想法也是一个成功的想法，被广泛采用。
so, that idea also, was a successful idea and widely adopted.
好的，这是基本架构，
Okay, so this is the basic architecture,
我将继续谈论一些方式和原因，
I'm going to go on and talk about some ways and reasons
为什么这个有吸引力，
why this might be attractive,
但首先是高层次的问题，
but first are there any just kind of high-level questions about,
微内核是什么。
what it is I mean by micro kernel.
好的。
Okay.
那么，人们希望的是什么，
So, what is it that people are hoping for,
当他们开始构建微内核的时候。
when they started building micro micro kernels.
所以，一个很大的动机，
So, one big motivation,
尽管你不一定会看到它被写得很多，
although you wouldn't necessarily see it written down much,
这只是一种审美。
it's just a sense of aesthetics, right.
我想很多人都觉得
I think just a lot of people feel
像 Linux 内核这样庞大复杂的单一程序，
that huge complicated a single programs like like Linux kernel
并不是很优雅，
are just not very elegant,
当然，我们可以构建系统，
that surely we can build something
更小，更有针对性的设计，
that's much more much much smaller much more focused design,
而不是一个巨大的有随机不同功能的[袋子]，
isn't such a huge [grab bag] of random different features,
所以我觉得有一种强烈的审美，
so I think there was a strong sort of aesthetic feeling,
我们当然可以做得比大内核更好。
surely we can do better than big kernels.
但是还有其他更具体可以量化的东西，
But others are more specific things that you might be able to quantify
或者更小的内核可能更安全，
or something a kernel that's small might be more secure, right,
代码越少， bug 越少，
a few lines of code you have, probably fewer bugs you have,
更少有人利用其中的 bug 来破坏安全，
less chance of somebody be able to exploit one of those bugs to break security,
然后最极端的是，
and then the extreme of that,
你可以想象操作系统可以证明是对的，
you could imagine operating system that's actually provable provably correct,
有人可以写一份证明，
where somebody can sit down and write a proof,
操作系统没有 bug ，
that the operating system has no bugs
或者做它应该做的事，其他什么也不做。
or does exactly what it's supposed to do and nothing else.
并且确实有一个，
And indeed there is at least one
证明是正确的，证明是安全的操作系统，叫做 seL4 ，
verified, proved correct, proved secure operating system named seL4,
它是 L4 微内核的众多后代之一，
which is one of the many descendants of the L4 micro kernel,
今天的论文，
today's paper,
人们知道，
but you really you know people know
如何验证中小型程序，
how to verify small to medium sized programs,
但他们不知道如何验证巨大的程序，
but they don't know how to verify huge programs
除非微内核很小，
unless the fact that micro kernels are small,
一种关键的因素，能够证明它们是正确的。
sort of critical ingredient and be able to prove their correct.
你喜欢小的另一个原因是，
Another reason why you might like small is that
少量代码通常更容易优化，
small amount of code is often like easier to optimize,
跟大型程序比起来。
than, than a huge program.
另一个小的可能更快原因是，
Another reason why small might result in fast is that
你不必为很多你不用的功能考虑，
you don't have to pay for a lot of features you don't use,
微内核几乎不做任何事情，
you know micro kernel does hardly anything,
那么你不必关心很多你不会使用的功能。
then you're not paying for a lot of features you're not using.
另一个小的原因是，
Another reason for small is that,
小内核可能会产生更少的设计决策，
small kernel probably bakes in far fewer design decisions,
让应用程序编写者做出更少的设计决策，
forces fewer design decisions on application writers
所以，它给他们留下了更多灵活性，
and so it leaves them more maybe leaves them more flexible flexibility
让他们做自己的设计决策。
to make their own design decisions.
顺便说一句，所有这些，
By the way, these are all,
这些不是微内核方法的必然结果，
these are not necessary consequences of the micro kernel approach,
这些都是人们希望通过使用微内核来实现的。
these are things that people hoped for and tried to achieve by using micro kernels.
另一些原因，
And another set of reasons,
微内核看起来很有吸引力与这样一个事实有关，
why micro kernels seemed attractive has to do with the fact that
很多代码都是用户级别的，
a lot of the code was at user level,
很多特性和功能，
that is a lot of features and functions,
我们在内核中使用的，
that we sort of grown used to being inside the kernel
实际上是用户级别的服务，
were actual user level services,
所以他们希望通过打破内核部分，
so they hope that by a sort of breaking the kernel part
运行不同的部分，比如用户级服务，
and running the different parts, like a user level services,
比如文件服务，文件服务服务器，
like a file service, for file service server,
这可能会使代码更加模块化，
that might cause the the code to be more modular,
可能会鼓励操作系统设计人员
might sort of encourage operating system designers
将所有这些功能划分为许多单独的服务，
to split up all these functions into many separate services,
那也许是一件好事。
that might that might be a good thing.
用户级代码也可能更容易修改，
User level code is also possibly easier to modify,
用户级别通常更容易调整，替换或修改，
its user level it's usually easier to tweak it or replace it or modify it,
比起在内核中做同样的事情，
than doing the same stuff in the kernel,
所以也许它更容易定制，
so maybe it's easier to customize,
将操作系统置于用户级别，
putting the operating systems at user level,
这也可能使它们更健壮，
that also might make them more robust,
如果内核出了问题，
you can, you can if the kernel something goes wrong with the kernel,
通常你收到 panic 然后重启，
you know, usually you have to panic and reboot,
因为，你不能再相信内核里的东西了，
because, you know you can't necessarily trust what's in the kernel anymore,
如果它有一些 bug ，
if it's had some bug,
可能会导致它覆盖其数据的随机部分，
that maybe causes it to overwrite a random part of its data,
如果你有一堆用户级别的服务，
whereas if you have a bunch of user level services
它们中的一个发生故障，
and one of them malfunctions
除零操作，或这释放野指针，
and devised by zero or dereferences a wild pointer,
也许只有那台服务器崩溃，
maybe only that one server will crash
让操作系统的其他部分完好无损，
and leaving the rest of the operating system intact,
然后也许你可以重启它，
then maybe you can restart it,
只重启那一台服务器，
just that one server,
所以，也许将操作系统功能移动到用户级进程，
so maybe user level, moving OS functionality to user process
可能会带来更强的健壮性，
might lead to more robustness,
这是令人惊讶的，
this is surprise,
特别是对驱动程序来说，
particularly evident for drivers,
内核中或硬件设备驱动程序中存在大多数 bug ，
there most bugs in the kernel or actually hardware device drivers,
如果我们能设法将设备驱动程序移出内核，
if we can manage to move the device drivers out of the kernel,
那么我们在内核中崩溃的 bug 可能会少得多。
then we might have many fewer bugs crashes in the kernel.
而最后一个好处，
And the final advantage,
人们想的是，
the people were thinking about back then is that,
你可以模拟一个或多个操作系统，
you could emulate one or multiple operating system [personalities]
在一个微内核上，
on top of a micro kernel,
所以，即使微内核几乎不直接为你做任何事情，
so even though micro kernel does does hardly anything for you directly,
你也可以运行 Unix 服务器或其他东西在它上面，
you might be able to run a Unix server or something on top of it,
可能在一台机器上不止一个。
maybe more than one on the same machine.
当然，这是今天的论文所说的，
Of course, that's what today's papers about,
在微内核上运行 Unix 或 Linux 作为服务，
running Unix, running Linux as a service on a micro kernel,
这些都是人们希望的东西，
these are all the set of things that people were hoping
能够获得一些[吸引力]，
to be able to get some [traction]
通过研究微内核设计。
on by looking into micro kernel designs.
当然会有一些难题，你必须想清楚，
Of course, there's some sort of puzzles, you have to think through,
一些挑战。
some challenges.
如果你想设计自己的微内核，一个挑战是，
One challenge, if you want to design your own micro kernel is
找出 API ，
actually figuring out you want the API
你希望微内核系统调用接口
you want the micro kernel system call interface
尽可能的简单，
to be as simple as possible,
因为关键是要让它变得很小，
because the whole point was to keep it small
什么是最小可以系统调用，
and what is the actual smallest set of useful system calls
你可以[使用]的，
you can get [away] with,
它看起来是什么样子的，
you know what does it look like,
这不是特别清楚，
that's not particularly clear,
看看最小的系统调用 API 。
look at the minimum system call API.
你需要最小系统调用 API ，
You need these this minimum system call API,
它越简单越好，
it's great to be simple,
但是你必须构建一些相当复杂的功能，
but you actually have to be able to build some pretty sophisticated features
在你的最小系统调用 API 之外，
out of your minimum system call API,
因为内核做的不够多，
because even the kernel doesn't do much,
最终，你必须能够运行程序，
you know in the end, you've got to be able to run programs,
你可能试着在微内核上运行 Unix ，
you got maybe you're trying to run Unix on top of a micro kernel,
为了能够执行 fork mmap 之类的操作，
to be able do things like fork mmap,
所以作为系统调用接口的一部分，
so as part of the system call interface,
简单低级系统调用接口，
simple low-level system call interface,
它必须足够强大，
it has to be powerful enough
以支持人们需要做的所有事情，
to support all the stuff people need to do,
比如 exec 和 fork ，
like exec and fork
甚至可能是写入时复制 fork
and hack maybe even copy-on-write fork
或磁盘文件的内存映射，
or memory mapping on disk files,
但这些都在一个没有文件系统的内核中，
but all in a kernel that has no idea about files or file system,
需要支持 exec ，
needs to support exec,
但内核对文件一无所知。
but with kernel that knows nothing about files.
我们需要操作系统的其他部分，
We need the rest of the, the operating system,
以某种方式确保微内核可能非常简单，
somehow ensure that micro kernel maybe very simple,
但是现在我们需要开发一些用户级的服务，
but you know now we're requiring the development of some set of user level servers,
实现操作系统的其他部分，
that implement the rest of the operating system,
所以我们至少要做到这一点，
so we need, that has to get done at least
可能需要解决一些设计难题，
and may require some solving design puzzles,
最后，这种安排需要大量通信，
and finally, the you know this arrangement requires a lot of chitchat
通过 IPC 进程间通信，
over inter processor communication over IPC,
所以会有很大的压力让 IPC 非常快，
so there's going to be great pressure to make the you know IPC very fast,
所以，需要知道 IPC 是否能足够快，
so you know wonder whether IPC can be made fast enough,
让微内核保持竞争力。
to keep micro kernels competitive.
好的，一般说来，
Alright, and just in general,
不仅仅是 IPC 的速度，
actually the not just IPC speed,
但总的来说，
but in general,
有很多理由相信宏内核可以获得一定的性能，
a lot of reason to believe that monolithic kernels derived some performance
因为它们是集成的，
out of the fact that they're integrated,
文件系统代码可以与虚拟内存代码和内存分配代码交互，
that the file system code can talk to the virtual memory code and memory allocation code,
它是一个[快乐的]大项目。
it's all sort of one big happy giant program.
如果将所有这些内容拆分到单独的服务中，
And if you require all those things to be split out into separate servers
或者可能拆分到内核和用户级别，
or may be split between the kernel and user level,
通过集成的方式进行优化的机会可能较少，
there may be fewer opportunities for optimization by way of integration,
然后可能会也可能不会损害性能。
then that may or may not end up hurting performance.
好的。
Alright.
所以这些都是期望的优势，
So these are sort of crosscutting hoped for wins
以及所有挑战，
and sort of challenges that all,
很多微内核项目所面对的。
the many micro kernel projects faced.
因为今天的论文，
Because of today's paper,
我要告诉你们一些关于 L4 的事情，
I'm gonna tell you a bunch of about L4 specifically,
它是今天论文作者开发和使用的微内核。
which is the micro kernel the the authors of today's paper developed and used.
L4 当然不是最早的微内核，
L4 is not, it's certainly not the earliest micro kernel ever made,
但它是早期微内核之一，
but it's one of the sort of early micro kernels,
从 20 世纪 80 年代开始的所有工作中，
that came out of all the work in this starting in the 1980s
就工作原理而言，是相当有代表性的。
and it's fairly representative as far as how it works.
一些目标是，
There's been, it's a bit of a moving target was
它发展和演变了很多年，
the subject of [intense] development and evolution for many years
而且它仍然很强劲，
and it's still going strong,
如果查看维基百科上，
if you look at on Wikipedia,
你会发现 L4 有 15 到 20 种不同的变体，
you'll see that there's maybe 15 or 20 different variants of L4,
它们来了又走，有些还在这里，
that have come and gone and some are still here,
我想从 20 世纪 80 年代末开始，
starting I think in the late 1980s
我要向你们解释的是
and I know what I'm gonna try to explain to you is
我对 L4 如何工作的理解，
my understanding of how L4 worked,
在今天的论文发表的时候。
at about the time today's paper came out.
好的，那么从高的层面来说，
Alright, so just at a high level,
L4 当然是微型的，
the L4 was certainly micro,
从某种意义上说，它是一个小内核，
in the sense that it was actually is a small kernel,
它只有 7 个系统调用，
it has only 7 system calls,
有些有点复杂，
some of them a little bit complex,
但它仍然只有 7 个系统调用，
but still it only has 7 system calls,
而今天的 Linux ，我最后一次统计时，有三百多个，
whereas today's Linux, the last time I counted, had in the mid three hundreds
甚至 xv6 是一个非常简单的内核，
and even xv6 which is an extremely simple kernel,
即使 xv6 也有 21 个系统调用，
even xv6 has 21 system calls,
所以 L4 只有 7 个，
so L4 it's only 7,
所以通过这个度量很简单，
so by that metric is simple,
它也不是很大，
it's also not very big,
我认为，当这篇论文写成时，大约有 13000 行代码，
I think, as the time this paper was written at about 13 000 lines of code,
只是没有太多，
just not too much,
xv6 比这更小，
xv6 is smaller than that,
我认为 xv6 内核可能有 6000 到 7000 行代码，
I think xv6 maybe six or 7000 lines of code in the kernel,
但就内核而言， xv6 仍然非常简单，
but still xv6 is very simple as kernels [],
L4 并不比这更复杂，
L4 not much more complex than that,
这是 Linux 的十分之一、二十分之一或三十分之一，
and this is you know a tenth or twentieth or thirtieth as big as as Linux,
是相当小的。
is pretty small.
它只有几个基本的抽象，
It had only a few basic abstractions,
它有任务或地址空间的概念，
it had a notion of what they called tasks or address spaces,
这些或多或少对应于我们在 Unix 中所说的进程，
and these more or less correspond to what we would call a process in Unix,
这是一堆从 0 开始的内存映射，
it's a bunch of memories map starting at 0
你可以在这里执行，
and and you're able to execute in here,
就像在进程中，
just like in the process,
与 xv6 的不同之处是，
when different from xv6 is that
每个任务可以有多个线程，
there can be multiple threads per task,
L4 负责在每个任务中调度多个执行线程。
and L4 was in charge of scheduling multiple threads of execution within each task.
这样的部分原因是
And part of the reason for this is
它有线程非常方便，
just it's very convenient to have threads
将线程作为编程结构化工具，
as a programming structuring program structuring tool
它也是，
and it was also,
我不知道他们是否支持多核机器，
I don't know if they actually supported multi-core multiprocessor machines,
在写这篇论文的时候，
at the time the paper was written,
但是，他们很可能有线程，
but, they may well have and threads,
当然，你需要能够
of course just what you need to be able to
利用多个核心执行同一个程序，
harness multiple cores executing the same program,
所以 L4 内核支持线程。
so there's are threads supported by L4 kernel.
所以， L4 支持任务，
So so, L4 supported tasks,
它知道任务，它知道线程，
it knew about tasks, it knew about threads
它也知道地址空间，
and it also knew about address spaces,
在这个意义上，你可以告诉 L4 ，
in the sense that you could, you could ask tell L4,
这是我们想要的页面映射到地址空间。
look, here's how we want pages mapped into address space.
L4 知道的另一件主要事情是进程间通信，
And the other main thing that L4 knew about is inter process communication,
每个线程都有一个标识符，
so that was every thread has an identifier
一个线程可能会说，
and one thread could say,
我想发送一条消息，
look, I want to send a message,
它只是给另一个线程几个字节，
it just some bytes to another thread,
这是这个标识符，
and here's this identifier,
请给另一个线程发送一条消息。
please, please send a message to that other thread.
所以，这些是任务，线程，地址空间和 IPC ，
So these are really the only task, threads, address spaces and IPC
实际上是唯一的抽象概念，
were really the only abstractions,
系统调用，
the system calls,
我不知道是否能把它们全部列出来，
I don't know if I can be able to list them all,
但是，系统调用是，
but the system calls were,
这里有一个线程，
there was a thread,
线程创建系统调用，
thread create system call,
你给它一个地址空间 id ，创建一个新的线程，
which also you gave it a address space id has to create a new thread
如果地址空间分配已经存在，
and if the address space are tasked in already exist,
它会给你创建一个新的任务，
it would create a new task for you,
将线程和任务创建结合在一起。
sort of combine thread and task creation.
有发送和接收，
There's send and receive,
不同风格的发送和接收 IPC 系统调用。
various flavors of send and receive IPC system calls.
有一种方法将页面映射到你的或其他地址空间，
There's a way to map pages into your or other address space,
所以你可以让 L4 改变你的地址空间的设置方式，
so, you, you could ask the L4 to change the way your address space was set up,
你的页表映射的设置方式，
the way your page table maps were set up,
但是你也可以要求 L4 ，
but you could also ask L4,
如果你有正确的权限，
if you had the right permissions to go
可以更改另一个任务的地址空间的设置方式。
and change the way another task's address space was set up.
因此，这实际上是通过 IPC 完成的，
So, this was actually done through the IPC,
将通过 IPC 接口，
would spent through the IPC interface,
将发送一个特殊的 IPC 消息，
you know would send a special IPC message,
内核知道目标线程，
that the kernel knew about to the target thread,
并且内核将修改目标线程地址空间。
and the kernel would modify the target thread's address space.
这是如果你创建一个新的线程，
And this is if you are creating a new thread,
实际上新创建的线程完全没有内存，
this is actually new threads are created with no memory at all,
所以如果你想创建一个线程，
so if you want to create a thread,
你首先调用线程创建系统调用
you first call the thread create system call
来创建新的线程，任务和地址空间，
to create a new thread and task and address space,
然后你发送它，
and then you send it,
如果你创建一个神奇的 IPC ，
if you make one of these magic IPCs
来发送一些你自己的内存映射，
to send some of your own memory maps of your own memory,
你已经准备好的指令或数据，
that you've prepared with instructions or data
为了将内存映射到新的，
to map that memory into the new,
新的任务地址空间，
and so a new task address space,
然后发送一个特殊的 IPC 到这个新的任务，
and then you send a special start IPC to this new task
通过程序计数器和你想开始执行的堆栈指针，
with the program counter and stack pointer you want it to start executing with,
它将开始执行，
that will start executing
并在要求启动程序计数器处设置内存。
and that memory you've setup at the program counter you ask startup.
有一种方法不通过系统调用，
There's a way not through system calls,
事实上，我不知道它是怎么工作的，
in fact I don't know how it worked,
但是特权任务可以映射设备硬件，
but privileged tasks could map device hardware,
映射设备控制寄存器到它们自己的地址空间。
you know device control registers into their own address spaces.
所以， L4 对设备不是很了解，
So, L4 didn't really know much about devices
比如磁盘或网卡，
like disks or network interface cards,
但是用户级软件可以直接访问，
but user level software could get directly at,
用户级软件可以实现设备驱动，
user level software that implemented device drivers,
用户级软件可以直接访问设备硬件。
that user level could get directly at device hardware.
有一种方法可以，
There was a way to
你可以告诉 L4 打开中断，
you could tell L4 to turn on interrupt,
来自任何设备的任何中断，
any interrupt from any device,
L4 并不知道哪台设备打开。
L4 didn't really know which device just turned,
把中断给 IPC 消息。
given interrupt into an IPC message.
所以设备驱动程序任务不仅读写设备硬件，
So a device driver task not just read write the device hardware,
也会告诉 L4 在设备中断的时候，
but also tell L4 well anytime that device interrupts,
请给我发送一条 IPC 消息，
please send me an IPC message,
通知我中断。
notifying me the interrupt.
最后，一个任务告诉内核
And finally one task tell the kernel
给它另一个任务页面错误的通知，
to give it notifications of another task page faults,
所以，如果这个任务出现页面错误，
so if this task page fault,
L4 会将其转换为 IPC 消息，
L4 would turn that into an IPC message
并将它发送到另一个专用的分页任务，
and send it to another designated pager task,
将页面错误通知发送给指定的页面任务，
send the notification the page fault to a designated pager task,
所以每个任务都有一个关联的分页任务，来处理它的页面错误，
so every task has an associated pager task, that handled its page faults,
这就是你把钩子挂在页面错误上的方式，
and that's the way you know you get hooks into the page faults,
用来实现写入时复制， fork 或懒分配。
in order to implement things like copy-on-write fork or lazy allocation.
内核就是这样，在 L4 中没有其他东西，
And that's it for the kernel, there's nothing else in L4,
没有文件系统，
there's no file system,
L4 本身并不支持 fork exec 之类的功能，
L4 didn't itself had support for things like fork exec,
除了这些非常简单的 IPC 之外，没有任何通信，
didn't have any communication beyond these very simple IPC,
比如没有管道，
like did not pipes,
没有设备驱动程序，
did not device drivers,
没有网络支持，什么都没有，
no networking support nothing,
如果你需要其他东西的话，
everything else if you wanted it,
你需要提供作为用户级别的服务。
you need to supply as a user level services.
好的，那么一件事是，
Okay, so one thing that are,
L4 支持线程切换，
L4 does supply is switching among threads,
L4 执行调度和上下文切换，
L4 would actually do the scheduling and context switches
以便在多个线程中复用单个 CPU ，
in order to multiplex a single CPU among multiple threads
你会发现它做的方式完全不令人惊讶，
and the way it did it you would find completely unsurprising,
L4 为每个线程、每个任务保存了寄存器，
L4 basically had saved registers for every task, for every thread,
当它执行线程时，
when it executed a thread,
执行线程会跳入用户空间，切换页表，
the executing thread would jump into user space, switch page tables,
所以，那个线程将在用户空间中执行一段时间，
so that thread and that thread will execute for a while in user space,
然后可能定时器中断响起，
then maybe the timer interrupt would go off
这是 L4 所知道的一种设备，
and that was actually a device L4 knew about,
定时器中断会在一段时间后触发，
the timer interrupt might go off after a while,
中断 L4 ，
interrupting the L4,
L4 将保存这个任务的用户寄存器到任务中，
L4 would save this task's user registers in a per task,
一个任务线程数组结构，
an array of tasks thread structures,
会将这个线程寄存器保存起来，
would save this threads registers away,
从循环中选择一个新任务运行，
pick a new task to run in a loop,
这与 xv6 中的调度循环非常像，
much like the scheduling loop in xv6,
从先前保存的寄存器恢复这个任务的寄存器，
restore this task's registers out from its previously saved registers,
切换页表，
switch page tables,
然后跳到这个任务，并执行一段时间，
and then jump into this task and execute it for a while,
直到定时器中断停止
until the timer interrupt went off
或直到这个任务 yield ，
or until this task either yielded,
我想这里可能还有一个 yield 系统调用或类似的调用。
I think there's also probably a yield system call or something like it.
一个任务可能会让出 CPU ，
A task can yield a CPU
或者任务可能会等待接收 IPC ，
or a task could wait to receive an IPC,
在这种情况下，
in that case,
我们跳回 L4 ，
L4, we jump back into L4
L4 看到寄存器切换到新任务并运行，
and L4 see this registers switch to a new task and run task,
所以 L4 的线程切换部分是非常熟悉的。
so that thread switching part of L4 is very, be very familiar.
那个。
The.
我之前提到过这件事，
I I mentioned this before,
我想说，因为它出现了，
I just want to because it comes up,
我想写在这里，
I wanna write here,
这个分页的概念，
this notion of a pager,
如果进程出现页面错误，
the, repeat if a process is a page fault,
trap 出现在内核，
traps into the kernel,
并且内核将页面错误转换为 IPC 消息，
and the kernel turns that page fault into an IPC message
发给指定的分页任务，
to a designated pager task
并告诉它地址，
and tells it the address,
告诉这个分页任务，
tells this pager task
哪个线程出了故障，以及它在哪个地址上出了故障。
which thread faulted and the address it faulted on on.
然后分页任务，
And then the pager task,
如果它想实现懒分配，
if it wants to say implement lazy allocation,
也许这个线程写入一些没有分配的内存，
maybe this thread write some memory that was not allocated yet,
我想它要求懒分配，
but I think that it sort of asked to be lazily allocated,
它的分页任务将负责从 L4 分配一些内存，
its pager task would then be in charge of allocating some memory from L4,
发送一个特殊的 IPC ，
sending one of these special IPCs,
导致内存映射到这个任务中，
cause that caused memory to be mapped into this task,
然后发送 IPC 以恢复这个线程的执行。
and then sending an IPC to resume execution inside this thread.
所以就有了分页任务的概念，
So there was this notion of pager task
来实现所有事情，
to implement all this all the stuff,
xv6 或 Linux 在页面错误处理程序中实现的，
that xv6 or Linux implements in page fault handlers,
你可以用这个实现写入时复制 fork ，
like you could implement copy-on-write fork with this,
如果你喜欢的话，
if you liked,
或这内存映射文件，
or memory mapped files,
它们都使用这些分页任务中的一个。
all using one of these pager task.
它们是一种强大的用户级方式，
They were sort of powerful user level way,
使用页面错误驱动的技巧。
play tricks with a driven by page faults.
所以这是一个例子，
And so this is an example,
许多例子中的一个，
one of many examples,
像 L4 这样的微内核可能更灵活，
in which micro kernel like L4 might have been quite a bit more flexible
对于用户程序来说，
for user programs
跟传统内核比起来，
than a conventional kernel,
比如，如果你让 Linux 做一些额外的事情，
like if you think Linux ought to do some extra thing,
比如，可能一些，
like maybe you know some you know,
如果 Linux 没有写入时复制 fork ，
if Linux didn't already have copy-on-write fork
而你想要写入时复制 fork ，
and you wanted to have copy-on-write fork,
如果不修改内核，就无法在 Linux 中实现它，
you really can't implement that in Linux without modifying the kernel,
而且没有办法为 Linux 编写可移植的代码，
and there's no way to write portable code,
可移植的用户级代码，
portable user level code for Linux,
它可以实现写入时复制 fork 之类的东西。
that could implement something like copy-on-write fork.
这并不完全正确，
That's not quite true,
但这是非常困难的，
but it would be very difficult,
而 L4 相对简单，
whereas L4 its relatively straightforward,
L4 已完全为你设置好，
L4 is completely set up for you
以便你能编写用户级代码，
to be able to write user level code,
它获取页面错误用来实现写入时复制 fork ，
that gets the page faults that are required to drive copy-on-write fork,
所有都在用户空间中，而不必扰乱内核。
all in user space, without having to mess with the kernel.
好的，关于 L4 如何工作，有没有什么问题？
Okay, so any questions so far about how L4 works.
哦，抱歉，你能解释一下线程和任务的区别吗？
Oh, sorry, can you just clarify the difference between a thread and a task?
是的，任务对应于，
Yes, a task corresponds to
它就像 xv6 中的进程，
it's like a process in xv6,
它有一些内存和地址空间，
it has a bunch of memory and address space
你可以在其中执行用户代码，
and you can execute user code in it,
如果你在 xv6 中有一个进程，
xv6 if you have a process in xv6,
那么它只能有一个控制线程，
it can only, it can only be one thread of control,
在一个 xv6 中的进程内执行，
on a single you know executing inside a process in xv6,
但是在现代操作系统和 L4 中，
but in modern operating systems and L4,
在单个进程中，在单个地址空间中，
in a single process, in a single address space,
如果你有多个内核，
you could have if you have multiple cores,
你可以让多个内核执行单个任务，
you can have multiple cores executing a single task,
通常每个核心都在任务的地址空间内设置自己的堆栈。
for each, typically always each set up with its own stack inside that task's address space.
所以，如果，
And so if,
这意味着你可以，
that means you can,
比如，编写一个程序可以获得并发速度，
for example write a single program that can get parallel speedup,
通过多核硬件增加性能，
improve performance from multi-core hardware
通过多个线程每个运行在一个核心上，
by running one thread on having multiple threads each running a different core,
从而完成更多工作。
thereby getting more work done.
好的，我明白了，谢谢。
Okay, I see, thank you.
好的。
Yes.
好的，如你所见，
Okay, so as you can see,
这是一个严重依赖 IPC 的设计，
this is a design that relies heavily on IPC,
因为你要与你的文件服务器交互，
because you're going to want to talk to your file server,
文件服务器想要与设备驱动器服务器交互，
a file server is going to want to talk to the device driver server,
你会看到 IPC 信息来回飞来飞去，
you're gonna have IPC messages flying back and forth,
对于每个系统调用，对于每个页面错误，对于每个设备中断，
for every system call, for every page fault, for every device interrupt,
IPC 系统需要速度非常快，
the IPC system just has to be fast,
现在我们开始讨论
however now we're starting to talk about
微内核故事中的一个严重的潜在缺陷。
a serious potential defect in a micro kernel story.
首先让我给你们展示一个简单但是非常慢的设计，
So first let me show you a straightforward but very slow design,
模仿 Unix 管道的 IPC ，
for IPC patterned off of Unix pipes
我之所以提到这一点，
and I'm bringing this up,
是因为一些早期的微内核以这种方式工作，
because some early micro kernels worked in sort of a similar way
与我即将向你们展示的类似，
to what I'm about to show you,
结果证明是很慢的。
which turned out to be slow.
好的，假设你有两个进程，
Okay, so let's suppose you have you know you have two processes,
我们有 P1 ，
we got P1,
P1 想要向 P2 发送消息。
P1 wants to send a message to P2.
那么这应该如何运作，
So how should that actually work,
一种可能是有一个 send 系统调用，
well, one possibility is to have a send system call,
你给 send 系统调用一个 id ，
and you give send system call the id
那个你想要发送消息的线程，
of the thread you want to send a message to
以及指向消息的字节的指针，
and a pointer to the message to the bytes,
可能是你想要发送到那个进程，
may be that you actually want to send to that process,
所以这个系统调用将跳转到内核，
so this system call are going to jump into the kernel,
也许我们可以设计这种仿照管道和 xv6 的方案，
you know maybe we design this patterned after pipes and xv6,
所以你可以想象有一个等待消息的缓冲区，
so you can imagine there being a buffer of messages waiting,
也许 P2 正在做其他的事情，
maybe P2 doing something else right now,
可能它是服务器，正在为别人的请求提供服务，
maybe it's a server, it's serving somebody else's request,
所以它还没有准备好处理你的请求，
so it's not ready to handle your request,
您可以想象，也许内核中有一个等待消息的缓冲区，
you can imagine, maybe a buffer of waiting messages in the kernel,
就像管道缓冲区一样，
like a pipe buffer,
当你调用 send 时，
when you call send,
它会将你的消息附加到这个缓冲区，
it appends your message to this buffer,
等待 P2 接收消息。
waiting for P2 to receive it.
事实上几乎总是，
You know, in fact almost always,
在这些系统中，你很少仅仅想要发送一条信息，
in these systems, you rarely just wanted to send a message,
你几乎总是想得到回应，
you almost always wanted to get a response too,
你需要 RPC ，远程过程调用操作，
you wanted an RPC, remote procedure call operation,
所以， P1 可能会紧跟其后的是接收，
so, in fact P1 would probably follow this immediately by a receive
以尝试获得响应，
to try to get the response back,
但总的来说，
but in general,
让我们暂时设想一下我们正在进行单向 IPC ，
let's just imagine we're doing a one-way IPC for the moment,
所以 send 会将你的消息附加到内核缓冲区中，
so send would append your message to the in kernel buffer,
我们必须将消息字节从用户空间复制到这个缓冲区，
we have to copy the message bytes from user space into this buffer
然后返回，进程一可以做一些其他事情，
and then return and process one can do something else,
比如可能准备接收回复，
like maybe prepared to receive the response,
过了一会儿，
after a while,
P2 想要接收下一条消息，
P2 it's gonna want to receive the next message
只要调用 recv 系统调用，
just gonna make the recv system call,
它将返回发送者的 id ，
and that's gonna return the id of the sender,
并将消息复制到 P2 的内存中，
and copy the message into P2's memory,
把前面的消息从队列里拿出来，
just gonna take the front message off the queue,
复制到 P2 的内存里，
copy into P2's memory,
然后返回。
and then return.
所以。
So.
这个叫做，
This is called,
有一些词来形容这个，
there's some words for this,
你会在今天的论文中看到，
whose [] you'll see saw in today's paper,
这称为异步方案，
this is called an asynchronous scheme,
因为 P1 发送消息而不需要等待任何东西，
because P1 sends a message without having to wait for anything,
它只是追加到队列并返回，
it just appends to queue and returns,
它被称为缓冲系统，
and it's called a buffered system,
因为内核复制这个消息到缓冲区中，
because the kernel copy this message into the buffer
到 send 的内部缓冲区中，
into its internal buffer on the send
然后稍后当接收发生时，
and then later when the receive happens,
它将消息从缓冲区复制到目标，
it copies the message out of the buffer to the target,
所以这是异步缓冲。
so this is asynchronous buffered.
如果你正在进行完整的请求响应对，
If you're doing a full request response pair,
然后 P1 将调用 send ，
then P1 is going to call send,
send 将会返回，
send going to return,
然后 P1 直接，
P1 is then immediately,
让我们假设这两组缓冲区，
let's assume we're going to assume that's really two sets of buffers,
每个方向一组，
one for each direction,
P1 立即调用 recv ，
P1 immediately gonna call recv,
recv 将等待某些内容出现在应答缓冲区中，
recv gonna wait, need to wait for something to appear in the reply buffer,
所以它不得不让出 CPU ，
so it's going to have to yield the CPU,
它会做一些事情，
it's got to do something
在 xv6 中，调用 sleep 并让出 CPU ，
and call sleep in xv6, yield the CPU,
在单个 CPU 系统上，
on a single CPU system,
可能只有在这一点上，
it may be only at this point,
P1 放弃 CPU ， P2 才可以运行。
that P1 gives up the CPU and now P2 can run.
事实上，这个时代的硬件几乎都是单核的，
And indeed the hardware in this era was almost always single core,
当然，这篇论文是在单核硬件上运行的，
certainly this paper is running on single core hardware,
所以 P1 将会，
so P1 is gonna,
P1 执行， P1 不执行，
P1 executing and P1 not executing
直到 P1 最终获得 CPU ，
until P1 finally gets up the CPU
recv 等待这里出现的消息，
and recv waiting for a message to appear here
并且只有到那时， P2 才能被调度，调用 recv ，
and only then will P2 be scheduled maybe to call recv,
recv 复制消息，
recv copy the message
然后 P2 调用它的 send ，
and then P2 make it's called to send,
追加其回复。
to append its reply.
然后 send 系统调用返回到 P2 ，
And then the send system call return to P2
在某一时刻， P2 可能会让出 CPU ，
and at some point, presumably P2 will give up to CPU,
可能是计时器响起，
maybe the timer will go off,
然后 P1 将在内核中恢复执行，
then P1 will resume execution in the kernel,
看到那里有一条消息，
see there's a message there
然后返回到用户空间，
and return back to user space
所以这意味着，
and so that means that,
这个设计是缓慢的设计。
this design is slow design.
为了得到请求和响应，
There's in order to have a request and a response,
需要四个系统调用，两个 send ，两个 recv ，
there's four system calls, two sends, and two recvs,
每一次用户内核穿越，
you know each user kernel crossings,
每一次都相当昂贵，
each one of which is reasonably expensive,
这里需要休眠，
there's a need to sleep,
这个 recv 必须休眠，等待数据出现，
this recv has to sleep, waiting for data to appear,
有一个完整调用调度器循环，
and there's a full call the scheduler loop
以及从 P1 到 P2 的上下文切换，
and a context switch from P1 to P2,
才能实现这个。
in order to make this.
每个内核穿越和上下文切换都可能是昂贵的，
And you know each of these kernel crossings and context switch is potentially expensive,
因为你每次跨越内核用户边界时，
because you know every time you cross the kernel user boundary,
你交换页表，
you switch page tables
那个，
and that is,
它几乎肯定会扰乱 CPU 缓存，
it has a near certainty of disturbing the CPU caches,
比如更改页表，
like changing the page table,
可能会刷新 TLB ，虚拟内存查找缓存，
probably flushes the TLB, the virtual memory lookup cache,
这会让事情变慢。
which is going to slow things down.
所以，这是一种相当慢的方式，
So, this is a pretty slow way to go
涉及大量内核穿越消息，
involves a lot of kernel crossings message,
在用户和内核之间复制消息，
copying of messages between user and kernel,
可能分配缓冲区等等，
maybe allocation of buffers etc,
但事实证明，
but it turns out that,
对于这个[]案例，
for the, for this [] case,
你发送请求，并且希望得到响应，
in which you're sending a request and you want to get a response back,
你可以将其简化为相当简单的设计，
you can strip this down to considerably simpler design
事实上，这就是它前进的方向。
and in fact, this is the way it forward.
这是在一份著名的论文上发表的，
And this was laid out in a famous paper,
称为通过内核设计改进 IPC ，
called improving IPC by kernel design
在今天的论文前几年发表。
published a few years before today's paper.
所以它做了几件不同的事情，
So it does a couple things differently,
首先，它是同步的。
for one thing, it's synchronous.
这就是，
That is,
这里没有丢弃任何东西，
there's none of this, there's no dropping something off
返回并等待，
and returning and waiting,
让另一个进程提取数据，
letting the other guy, letting the other process pick up the data,
它感觉像，
when it feels like,
不是 send 等待 recv 和 recv 等待 send 。
instead send waits for receive and receive waits for send.
所以， P1 想要发送，我调用 send ，
So, one process one and I want to send and I call send,
它不会将我的消息复制到缓冲区，
it doesn't copy my message into a buffer,
P1 现在直接，
it actually P1 will now immediately,
如果 P1 在 L4 内核中发送，
if the P1 send in the L4 kernel,
等待 P2 调用 recv ，
waits for P2 to call recv
并且如果 P2 已经在内核中等待调用 recv ，
and if P2 is already in the kernel waiting in a call to recv,
P2 要么已经在内核中，等待调用 recv ，
well P2 is either already in the kernel, waiting in a call to recv
或者 P1 send 并等待，
or P1 send and wait for it,
等待 P2 的下一个调用 recv ，
wait for P2's next call to recv,
当两者都到达这里时，
when both have arrived here,
当 P1 在内核中，它调用 send ，
when P1 is, in the kernel and it's called a send,
P2 在内核中，调用 recv ，
P2's in the kernel is called to recv,
只有那时才会有事情发生，
only then does anything happen,
这个速度快的原因之一是，
and one reason this is fast is that,
如果 P2 已经在 recv ，
if P2 is already in recv,
然后 P1 ，当它在内核中执行 send 时，
then P1, when it's executing send in the kernel,
可以没有上下文切换或通用调度，
can just without a context switch or a general purpose scheduling,
可以直接跳回 P2 的用户空间，
can just jump back into user space in P2,
就像是从这个 recv 返回，
as if it was returning from this receive, right,
这是一条通过内核的更快的路径，
and that's a much faster path through the kernel,
比起保存寄存器，放弃 CPU ，调用调度器，
than you know saving registers, giving up the CPU calling the scheduler
并找到一个新的进程来运行，
and finding a new process to run,
相反， P1 send 知道有等待的 recv ，
instead P1 send knows that there's a waiting recv,
然后立刻跳到了 P2 ，
and just sort of immediately jumps into P2,
就像它是从 recv 返回一样。
as if it was returning from recv.
他们开发的方案也是无缓冲的，
The scheme that they developed is also unbuffered,
它可以部分做到这一点，
and it could do that partially,
因为它是同步的，
because it's synchronous,
当 send 和 recv 都在内核中，
when both the send and recv are in the kernel,
信息可以，
the message can be,
send 发送一些信息，
you know send sending some message,
内核可以直接将消息从用户空间复制到用户空间，
the kernel can directly copy the message from user space to user space,
而不必首先复制到内核中，然后再从内核中返回，
without having to first copy into the kernel, and then back out of the kernel,
由于双方都在等待对方的系统调用，
because because since both sides wait for the other system call,
发生的事，
what happened,
这意味着它们在等待这两个指针已经知道，
that means that they've waited for both pointers to be known,
recv 指定它希望将消息存放在何处，
recv specifies where it wants the message to be deposited,
所以，在这一点上，
so at this point,
我们知道这两个地址，然后内核可以直接复制，
we know both addresses, then kernel just do the copy directly,
而不是通过内核。
instead of through the kernel.
如果消息非常小，
For and if the message is super small,
可能只有几十个字节，
like maybe only a few dozen bytes,
然后，它可以在没有任何复制的情况下在寄存器中传递，
then it can be passed in registers without any copy at all,
你可以称之为零拷贝。
what you might call zero copy.
请记住，只有当 P2 已经处于 recv 状态时， send 才会继续，
Remember the send only proceeds if the P2 is already in recv
send 直接跳转到 P2 ，
and send basically jumps directly to P2,
这条通过内核的代码路径
well this code path to the kernel
注意不会干扰一堆寄存器，
takes care to not disturb a bunch of registers
这意味着 P1 可以把它的系统调用，
and that means that P1 can put its system call,
如果消息很短，
if the message is short,
它可以把消息放在某些指定的寄存器中，
it can put the message in certain designated registers,
内核保证在 P2 之前保留这些寄存器，
the kernel guarantees to preserve those registers on its way up to P2
这意味着，
and that means that,
当内核作为 send 的结果从 recv 系统调用返回时，
when the kernel returns from the recv system call as a result of send,
这些指定寄存器的内容保存了那个消息，
the contents of those designated registers hold the message
根本不需要从一个内存复制到另一个内存，
and therefore never had to be copied at all from memory to memory,
根本不用移动，
never had to be moved at all,
它们只是在寄存器中，
they're just sitting right in the registers,
在那里它们可以非常快地被访问。
where they can be accessed very quickly.
这当然只适用于小信息，
And this you know of course only works for small messages,
对于非常大的消息， L4 可以在 IPC 消息中携带页面映射，
for very large messages, L4 can carry a page mapping in IPC message,
所以对于巨大的信息来说，
so for huge messages,
比如从文件里读取块之类的结果，
you know like the result of reading a block from a file or something,
你可以只发送将映射到目标地址空间的页面，
you could just send the pages will be mapped into the target address space,
同样不需要任何复制。
again without any copy.
所以它是通过页面映射来完成的，
And so it's done through page mapping,
提供页面，
give away the page
或提供访问权限以共享页面。
or access [], access to this permission to share the page.
所以小消息是快的，
And so small messages are fast,
大消息也是相当快的，
huge messages are pretty fast,
你仍然需要根据目标调整页表，
you still have to adjust the page table to target,
但这比复制要快得多。
but that's much faster than copying.
L4 玩的最后一个把戏是，
And final trick that L4 played was
注意，如果你正在对请求和响应执行 RPC ，
noticing that if you're doing an RPC with the request and response,
是非常程式化的对等的系统调用，
are very stylized peers of system calls
你也可以将系统调用合并起来，
and you may as well combine system calls
合并 send 和 recv 系统调用，以减少内核穿越，
send and recv system calls in order to reduce kernel crossing,
所以，对于 RPC 的特殊情况，
so for the special case of RPC,
这几乎总是人们在做的事情，
which is almost always what people are doing,
当他们使用 IPC 时，
when they're using IPC,
这里有一个 call 系统调用，
there was a call system call,
call 基本上是 send 加 recv 的组合，
and the call was basically combined send plus receive,
但是没有返回到用户空间，
but without the return to user space,
然后重新进入内核空间，
and then re-entry into kernel space,
这是一对系统调用执行的，
that a pair of system calls take,
在服务器端，
on the server side,
只有一个调用，
there was a a single call
可以发送来自一个系统调用的应答，
that would send the reply from one system call
然后等待来自任何人的下一次系统调用的请求消息。
and then wait for the request message from anyone for the next system call.
这是一个回应的发送，
And this is basically a send of one response,
但是等待接收下一个请求，
but wait to receive the next request,
这又一次将内核穿越的数量减少了一半，
and this again cut in half the number of kernel crossings
事实证明，
and it turned out that,
所有这些优化的总和，
the sum of all of these optimizations,
现在对于较短的 RPC ，
now for the kind of short RPCs
它是一个典型的工作负载，
which are you know one typical workload,
所有这些会导致加速 20 倍。
all this led to a 20x speedup.
这是他们的论文所说的，
This is what their paper reported,
比以前的系统快了 20 倍，
20x speedup over there previous system,
大概有点像我在之前的设计中展示的。
which was presumably a little bit more like what I showed in a previous design.
所以这是一个令人印象深刻的，
And so this was an impressive,
这篇论文是在几年前由一些相同的作者发表的，
this paper came out a few years before the by some of the same authors,
但在人们阅读之前的几年，
but few years before the people were reading,
这让人们对微内核有了更多的好感。
and this caused people to view micro kernels a little bit more favorably.
IPC 是可以相当快的。
The IPC could actually be quite fast.
关于 L4 玩的这些 IPC 技巧，有什么问题吗？
Any questions about these IPC tricks that L4 plays?
是的，我想我错过了这个，
Yeah, I I think I missed this,
但是，当进程发送有接收消息时，
but, when is a process sending there are receiving messages,
它什么时候在使用那个系统调用？
like when is it using that system call?
好的，实际上，对于 RPC ，对于请求响应，
Okay, actually, so for RPCs, for request response,
事实上，进程使用这对系统调用，
in fact, in fact, the the processes use this pair of of system calls
而不是 send 和 recv 。
rather than send and secv.
所以，是的， call 有两个参数，
So yeah, call you really get two arguments,
你要发送的消息和放置响应的位置，
message you want to send and a place to put the response
在内核内部，只是将这两者结合起来，
and inside the kernel just combines these two,
你可以认为这是一种 hack ，
you could view this is a bit of a hack,
但由于 IPC 非常频繁，
but because IPC is so frequent,
它值得使用一些 hack 来让它更快。
it's worth a little bit of hack in order to make it fast.
在上面的图表里，在方框中，
And in the diagram up there, in the box,
你让 P2 运行 recv 系统调用，
where you have P2 sending that are running the recv system call,
是什么促使 P2 。
why, what prompted P2 to.
好的，在我的 RPC 世界里，
Okay it in in my RPC world,
我们有客户端，
we got, we have clients,
它们向服务器发送请求，
and they're sending requests to servers,
服务器将做一些回应，
and the server is going to do something in reply,
所以既然 P2 是服务器，
so since P2 is the server,
我们想象 P2 处于 while 循环中，
we imagine that P2 is sitting in a while loop,
它将从任何客户端接收下一条消息，
in which, in which it's going to receive the next message from any client,
做一点工作来处理它，
do a little bit of work to process it,
在数据库中查找一些数据或其他操作，
you know look up some data in a database or something,
然后发送回复，
and then send a reply
返回到循环的顶部并再次等待，
and go back to the top of the loop and wait again,
所以最接近的情况是，
so to first [approximation],
我们希望 P2 会把所有的时间都花在等待来自任何人的下一条消息上，
we expect P2 spends all its time waiting for the next message from anyone,
可以从任何人那里请求。
that can request from anyone.
这个设计确实，
And this design really,
它有点依赖于 P2 ，
it does kind of rely on P2 always
当它在其他时间，
and when it's at rest,
就是在内核中，
basically sitting in the kernel
在一个 recv 系统调用上，等待下一个请求，
in a recv system call waiting for the next request,
所以下一个请求可以直接从该系统调用返回。
so that the next request can directly basically return from that system call.
这是一条捷径，
And that's the fast path,
在这个设计中是非常高效的。
that's super efficient in this design.
抱歉，我只是想跟进一下，
Sorry, just to follow up on that,
也就是说，
that means that,
你说它来自 P1 返回 P2 ，
you said that it goes from P1 and returns to P2,
所以想要回来，
so like to come back,
你需要回复，所以。
you would need to send a response, so.
是的，我们希望 P2 会发送一个响应，
That's right, we expect P2 to send a response,
并且响应的发送反向遵循基本相同的代码路径，
and that sending of the response actually follows basically the same code path in reverse,
当 P2 发送响应时，
that when P2 sends a response,
有效地使 P1 返回，
that that effectively causes P1 to return from,
我是说， P1 实际上是在调用 call 系统调用，
I mean, P1 was actually making this call system call,
所以， P2 响应的传递导致 call ，
so the delivery of P2's response causes the call,
返回从这个系统调用回到 P1 。
the return from this from this system call back into P1.
好的，我明白了，谢谢。
Okay, I see, thank you.
这与通常的设置略有不同，
This is a little bit different from the usual setup,
你认为可以跳转到内核和系统调用，
where you think you jump into the kernel and system call
你执行该系统调用，
and you execute that system call
它将返回代表 P1 的所有工作，
and it returns sort of all working on behalf of P1
这是管道读写工作的方式，
which is the way pipe read write work,
这里，你知道 P1 进入内核，
here, you know P1 is entering the kernel,
P1 进入内核，返回却是 P2 .
P1 entering the kernel,
and you know that the return goes to P2,
有点奇怪，但速度很快。
kind of odd, but very fast.
好的，所以这是对人们使用微内核的一种很大的贡献，
Okay, so this was a big big sort of contribution to people taking micro kernels,
人们愿意使用微内核
people's willingness to take micro kernel
作为宏内核的潜在替代品，
seriously as potential replacement for a monolithic kernels,
但是，你仍然需要解决这个问题，
however you know that you still have to still leave [] the question,
即使 RPC 很快，
even if RPC is fast,
比如你从哪里得到操作系统的其他部分，
like where you get the rest of the operating system,
内核只有百分之几的所有东西，
like this kernel only has a few percent of all the stuff,
比如文件系统和网络堆栈，
like file systems and network stacks,
我们希望使用完整的操作系统。
we expect to be in a full operating system.
其他的部分，我们该怎么办，
What do we do about the rest
这个问题通常在大学研究项目的背景下提出，
and this question is usually being asked in the context of some university research project
他们资源相对有限，
with relatively limited resources,
我们需要从某个地方获得所有这些用户级别的服务。
we need to get all those user level servers from somewhere.
实际上，有一些专门的应用程序，
Actually there are specialized applications
这不是一个太大的问题，
for which that's not too much of a problem,
如果我们运行的是某种设备，控制器，
if we're running you know some sort of device you know controller,
或者你的车的点火控制系统，
or maybe the you know ignition control system for your car,
这只运行了几千行代码，
that is only running a few thousand lines of code anyway,
可能只需要一个文件系统，
maybe just need a file system,
然后，我们可以在用户级别使用很少的东西，
then we can get away with very little stuff at user level
微内核对于这类应用来说完全是有意义的，
and micro kernels totally makes sense for that kind of application,
但是人们，
but but the people,
当这些项目真的有目标的时候，
you know when these projects really they had ambitions,
使用它完全取代现有的操作系统，
that oh gosh going to totally replace existing operating systems,
他们希望能构建一些东西，
and they hoped that they could build something,
人们想要在他们的工作站上运行的东西，
that people would want to run on their on their workstations
在他们的服务器上运行，无处不在，
and run on their servers and everywhere,
完全替换大的宏内核，
just replace big monolithic kernels altogether,
但是要做到这一点，你需要一个真正的，
and but for that you know you need a real,
你需要操作系统所能做的所有东西。
you need all the stuff that an operating system does.
一种可能性，更多是一种哲学上的可能性，
One possibility, the most maybe sort of philosophically consistent possibility
就是重新实现你需要的一切，
would be to re-implement everything you need,
而是以一种微内核的方式，
but in a sort of micro kernel way
就像大量不同的用户级进程，
as lots and lots of different user level processes,
但那只是，
but that's just,
实际上人们，有很多项目都是这么做的，
actually people, there were projects did that,
但这是一项繁重的工作，
but it's a vast amount of work
更具体地说，人们真的想运行，
and more specifically, people really want to run,
为了让我使用笔记本电脑，
you know, in order for me to use a laptop,
它必须运行 Emacs ，
it just has to run Emacs
它必须运行我最喜欢的 C 编译器，
and it has to run my favorite C compiler,
否则我绝对不会切换到你们的操作系统。
otherwise I'm just definitely not going to switch to your operating system.
这意味着微内核要想获得任何形式的采用，
And what that meant is that micro kernels in order for to gain any kind of adoption,
它们必须能够支持现有的应用程序，
they had to be able to support existing applications,
它们必须能够兼容，
they had to be able to be compatible,
提供完全相同的或者至少在更高级别的 API 上相同的系统调用，
provide identical or at least the system call at the higher level service API level,
它们必须完全兼容
they had to be totally compatible with
一些现有的操作系统，比如 Unix Linux ，
some exist operating system, like Unix like Linux,
为了让任何人都愿意换。
in order for anybody to be willing to switch.
所以这些项目面临着一个更具体的问题，
So these projects face a more specific problem of
它们将如何得到，
how they were going to get,
它们如何实现与现有应用程序的兼容性，
how are they going to attain compatibility with existing applications
为 Linux 或 Windows 或其他平台编写的应用程序，
written for Linux or maybe Windows or something,
但是对于这个项目来说，是 Linux ，
but for this project, it was Linux,
不是编写他们自己的全新的用户级服务器，
and rather than write their own totally new set of user level servers,
它们模仿 Linux ，他们决定走一条更容易的路，
they mimic Linux, they decided to take a far easier path
很多项目都是这样做的，
and many projects did this,
直接在他们的微内核上运行已有的宏内核，
of simply directly running an existing monolithic kernel as on top of their micro kernel,
而不是重新实现一些新的东西，
instead of re-implementing some new thing
这正是今天论文的主题。
and says that's exactly what today's paper is about.
事实上， L4 微内核在底部，
It has, indeed, you know L4 micro kernel down at the bottom,
但也像一个相当大的服务器，
but also as like a pretty big server,
它们将完整的 Linux 内核作为用户级进程运行，
they run a pretty full Linux kernel as a user level process,
这听起来可能有点令人惊讶，
and so, that may sound a little surprising,
内核不是用户级进程，内核就是内核，
the kernel is not a user level process right, the kernel is the kernel,
你认为它是在硬件上运行的，
you think of it as running on the hardware,
但实际上 Linux 内核，
but in fact you know Linux kernel
如你所见，在 QEMU 中运行 xv6 ，
as you can see from running xv6 in QEMU,
就是在用户空间中运行的，
which is running in user space after all,
内核只是一个程序，
a kernel is just a program
所以，只要稍加修改，
and so with some modifications,
它就可以在用户级别运行，
it can be made to run at user level,
所以他们必须修改 Linux ，
and so they had to modify Linux
他们在 Linux 中使用了很多低级的东西，
and they took a lot of the low-level stuff in Linux,
比如 Linux 中的代码，
for example of the code in Linux,
期望能够直接修改页表
that expects to be able to directly modify page tables
或读写处理器寄存器，
or read and write processor registers,
他们需要修改一些低级别的东西，
there were some low-level stuff they had to modify,
Linux 的某些部分必须改变，
some parts of Linux had to change,
为了将它们转换为进行系统调用，
in order to convert them to basically make system calls
或者通过 L4 发送 IPC 消息，而不是直接访问硬件，
or send IPC messages through L4 instead of directly get at hardware,
但在很大程度上，
but for the most part,
它们可以直接运行几乎所有 Linux ，而不需要修改，
they were able to directly run, without change, almost all of Linux,
所以这意味着他们得到 Linux 的一部分，
so that means they got as part of Linux,
文件系统和网络支持以及各种设备驱动程序，
you know file system and network support and all kinds of device drivers,
Linux 带来的东西，
who knows what that comes with Linux,
而不必编写他们自己的版本。
without having to write their own version of this.
事实上，这个设置的方式是，
You know, in fact the way this was set up was,
Linux 内核作为一个 L4 任务运行，
that Linux, the Linux kernel ran as one L4 task,
但是每个 Linux 进程作为单独的 L4 任务运行，
but each Linux process ran as a separate L4 task,
当您登录到这个 Linux 时，
when you log into this Linux
你让它为你运行一个 shell ，一个终端窗口或其他东西，
and you ask it to run a shell for you, a terminal window or something,
它将启动一个 L4 任务，
it's going to fire up an L4 task,
它将在用户级别运行 Linux 程序，
that's going to run that Linux program at user level,
所以这里 Linux 有一个任务，
so there were one task for Linux
以及在 Linux 下启动的每个 Linux 进程都有一个任务，
and one task for each Linux process that you fire up under Linux
Linux 不是直接修改 VI 进程使用的页表，
and Linux instead of directly modifying the page table the VI, VI process uses,
Linux 将发送写 IPC 给 L4 ，
Linux is going to ask send the write IPC to L4
以使 L4 修改 VI 的页表。
to cause L4 to change VI's page table.
关于这里的基本方案，有什么问题吗？
Any questions about that, about the basic scheme?
另一件事改变的事，
Another thing to, another thing that was changed,
很多小事都变了，
many small things were changed,
但是，有一件特别有趣的事情是，
but a specific thing of interest is that,
当 VI 想要进行系统调用时，
when VI wants to make a system call,
所以，如果 VI 不知道它在 L4 上运行，
so, if VI doesn't know it's running on L4,
在这个方案中，
in this scheme,
实际上所有这些程序认为自己运行在 Linux 上，
it's really all these programs just think of themselves as running on Linux,
当 VI 想要进行系统调用时，
when VI wants to make a system call,
L4 不支持的系统调用，
you know L4 does not support,
它不是在进行 L4 系统调用，而是进行 Linux 系统调用，
its not making L4 system call, it's making Linux system call,
所以 VI 系统调用，比如 fork ，
so VI system calls like fork,
这里有一个很小的库，链接到，
there's a little library, basically that was linked into these,
Linux 进程将返回调用，
Linux processes that would return calls
比如 fork exec pipe read 或 write 之类的调用，返回到 IPC 消息，
like things like fork or exec or pipe read or write into IPC messages,
它将发送到 Linux 任务，
that it would send to the Linux task
并等待 Linux 任务的响应，
and wait for the response the Linux task,
然后返回，像系统调用返回一样。
then return as if the system call returned.
所以，这些小库将系统调用返回到 Linux 的 IPC 消息中，
So so these little libraries return system calls into IPC messages to Linux
这意味着，
and what that meant is that,
如果 Linux 内核任务没有做任何事情，
if the Linux kernel task isn't doing anything, it isn't doing anything else,
它在一个 recv 调用上，等待接收下一个系统调用请求 IPC ，
it's sitting in a call recv， waiting for the next system call request IPC
来自这些进程中的任何一个。
from any one of these processes.
这导致了，
And that led to it,
这导致了明显的不同，
that that leads to a significant difference
这种 Linux 的工作方式与普通 Linux 的工作方式，
between how this Linux works and how ordinary Linux works,
在普通的 Linux 中，比如 xv6 ，
in ordinary Linux, just like xv6,
每个用户级进程都有一个对应的内核线程，
there's a basically a kernel thread that corresponds to every user level process
并且当程序进行系统调用时，
and when program makes a system call,
内核代表该系统调用运行一个线程，
the kernel runs a thread on behalf of that system call,
在普通 Linux 中，
and when in ordinary Linux,
当 Linux 在内核线程之间切换时，
when Linux switches between kernel threads,
这意味着从一个进程切换到另一个进程，
that basically implies a switch from one process to another,
所以这是一对一的关系，
so there's kind of one to one correspondence
Linux 内核运行的内核线程，
between what kernel thread Linux kernels running
和 Linux 完成后要运行的进程之间，
and what process is gonna run when Linux is done,
在这里，连接被打断了，
here that connection is broken,
实际上，这个 Linux 服务器中，
they were indeed in this Linux server,
一个内核线程对应于。
a kernel thread corresponding to each.
抱歉，让我再说一遍，
I'm sorry, let me start again,
Linux 内核服务器在单个 L4 线程中运行，
the Linux kernel server was running in a single L4 thread,
所以在 Linux 中一次只有一个控制线程在执行，
so there was only a single sort of thread of control executing in Linux at a time,
然而，就像在 xv6 中一样，
however, just as in xv6,
这个控制线程切换
this one thread of control would switch
使用非常类似于 xv6 上下文切换的技术，
using a technique very much like xv6 context switch,
可以在对应于每个用户进程的内核线程之间切换，
could switch between a kernel thread corresponding to each user process,
但是这些，
however, which of these,
这些内核线程纯粹在 Linux 内部实现的，
the these kernel threads were implemented purely within Linux,
与 L4 级线程无关，
had nothing to do with L4 threads,
这里只有一个 L4 线程，
there's only one L4 thread here,
但是哪个用户进程正在运行由 L4 确定，
but which user process was running was determined by L4,
所以在这个设置中，
so in this setup,
Linux 可能服务于执行 VI 的内核线程的请求，
Linux might be serving a request from executing the kernel thread for VI,
服务 VI 系统调用，
serving a VI system call,
同时， L4 引起 shell 在用户空间中运行，
at the same time that L4 is causing this shell to run in user space,
这与 xv6 或 linux 中的情况非常不同，
which is very unlike what happens in xv6 or Linux
在它们之中存在直接关系，
where there's a direct correspondence
在活动内核线程和相应的用户级线程之间，
between the sort of active kernel thread and the corresponding a user level thread,
在这里，L4 运行，
here L4 of running whatever
Linux 内核中的这些线程更加私有，
it feels like and these threads in the Linux kernel are really much more private
关于 Linux 能够并发执行系统调用，
and are just about Linux being able to concurrently execute system calls
在不同的执行阶段，
in different stages of execution,
可能一个进程正在等待磁盘，
where maybe one process is waiting for the disk in its thread,
Linux 可以运行不同进程内核线程来服务进程系统调用。
Linux can run a different processe's kernel thread to serve that process system call.
所以，你可能会想，为什么这个设计没有直接使用 L4 线程
So, you might wonder why this design didn't directly use L4 threads
来实现 Linux 内部的各种不同的内核线程，
to implement the various different kernel threads inside Linux,
为什么 Linux 实现自己的内部线程，
why did Linux implement its own sort of internal threads package
而不是使用 L4 线程，
instead of using L4 threads,
答案是，在那个时候，
and the answer was that in those days,
a ，他们没有多核硬件，
a, they didn't have access to multi-core hardware,
他们使用的是单核硬件，
they were using single core hardware,
所以，这里没有性能优势，
so there were no performance advantage
在内核中同时执行多个线程，
to be able to execute multiple threads in the kernel at the same time,
因为只有一个核心，
because there was only one core,
所以，第二个线程无法执行，
so a second thread couldn't be executing,
因为硬件的原因，一次只能执行一个线程，
only one thread could execute at a time due to the hardware,
另一个可能更有说服力的原因是，
and the other may be even more powerful reason is that
那时候，他们用的这个 Linux 版本，
in those days, the version of Linux they were using,
没有支持，
did not did not have the support,
这需要有多个线程，多个核心，
that's required to have multiple threads multiple cores
同时在内核内执行，
executing inside the kernel at the same time,
他们使用的是单处理器 Linux ，
they were using a uni-processor Linux,
足够老的 Linux ，它只有一个核心用于内核，
so old enough Linux, it expected only one core the kernel at a time,
它没有像 xv6 那样的自旋锁，
it didn't have things like the spin locks the xv6 has,
这允许在内核内正确执行多个多核，
that would allow it to correctly execute multiple multiple cores inside the kernel,
所以，不会有性能优势，
so there would have been no performance advantage
在内核内具有多个活动的 L4 线程，
in having multiple L4 threads active inside the kernel,
但它需要添加，
but it would have required adding in,
为了增加性能，
you know for you know performance,
添加自旋锁和其他内容，
when adding in all the spin locks and other stuff,
用来支持并发性，
that's required to support concurrency,
所以他们没有这么做。
so they didn't do it.
这种安排的一个缺点是，
A drawback of this arrangement is that,
在普通 Linux 中，在原生 Linux 中，
in ordinary Linux, in native Linux,
就像你直接在笔记本电脑上运行的，
like you would run directly on your laptop,
Linux 有很多复杂的调度机制，
Linux has a lot of sophisticated scheduling machinery,
可以对不同的进程设置优先级，
that can do things like impose priorities on different processes
或者保证各种公平，
or ensure various kinds of fairness,
这很好，因为在你的笔记本电脑上，
and that was fine, because in on your laptop,
因为 Linux 控制着每个核心上运行的进程，
because Linux is in control of what process is running on each core,
但在这个设置中， Linux 根本不能控制这一点，
but in this setup, Linux is not controlling that at all,
Linux 无法控制什么进程正在运行，
and Linux is no control over what, what process is running,
因为执行此调度的是 L4 ，而不是 Linux ，
because it L4 that does this scheduling, not Linux,
这些进程由 L4 调度，
you know these processes are scheduled by L4,
所以，他们失去了让 Linux 负责调度的能力。
so they kind of lost the ability to have Linux be in charge of a schedule.
这有点缺陷，
You know, it's a bit of a defect of this,
尽管我确信后来的 L4 版本有针对 Linux 或类似系统的某种方式，
although I'm sure later versions of L4 had some way for Linux or something like it
为了告诉 L4 调度器，
to be able to tell the L4 schedule,
请给这个进程更高的优先权或者别的什么，
look, please give this process higher priority or whatever,
所以这有点奇怪。
so it's a bit awkward.
好的。
Alright.
所以，他们花了这么多功夫才让这件事开始。
So, so they went to all this work to get this going.
而且，你应该问问自己，
And, you should ask yourself
这篇关于微内核的论文带给我们的教训是什么？
you know what is the, what's the takeaway lesson from from this paper about micro kernels.
有一件事，所以对我们来说，
You know one things, so for us,
这篇论文有很多有趣的花絮，
you know this paper has a lot of interesting tidbits,
关于微内核如何工作，
about how micro kernels work,
关于 Linux 如何工作，
about how Linux works
以及如何设置如何设计这样的系统，
and how you set up how you can design a system like this,
这可能很有趣，
which may be interesting,
但在一个更大的世界里，人们想要吸取一些教训，
but a larger world, people want to want to draw some lessons,
他们需要的，
they need to be able to,
我在这篇论文中介绍了一些经验教训，
I present some lessons in this paper,
论文没有真正回答微内核是不是一个好主意，
the paper is not really answering the question are micro kernel is a good idea,
这并不是这里真正发生的事情，
that's not really what's going on here,
这篇论文讨论了，
the paper what the paper is part of argument about
微内核是否有足够的性能来值得使用，
whether micro kernels have enough performance to, to be worth using
原因是，
and the reason is that
在这篇论文发表之前的五年或者十年，
in in maybe five years five or ten years before this paper came out,
有一个著名的测量结果，
there was a famous set of measurements,
在之前的一种称为 Mach 的微内核上，
on one of the predecessor micro kernels and earlier micro kernel called Mach,
基本上在这种配置下运行，
basically running in very much this configuration,
但这是不同的，内部设计完全不同，
but it's different, you know, totally different design internally,
但都是一样的架构。
but kind of the same architecture.
早先这个微内核项目的名字叫 Mach ，
This, the name of this earlier micro kernel project is Mach,
有对 Mach 的测量，
there was measurements on Mach,
表示 Mach 比普通 Unix 慢得多，
that showed that Mach was dramatically slower than just ordinary Unix,
当它在这个配置中运行时，
when it was run in this configuration
这有很多原因，
and you know there are a lot of reasons for that
必须使用 IPC 系统，
having to do with the IPC system,
并不像你希望的那样优化，
not being as optimized as you might hope,
它们是有更多地切换上下文，
they're being just sort of more context switches
使用内核穿越和高速缓存未命中等等，
and you know we use our kernel crossings and cache misses and whatever,
Mach 慢的原因有很多，
there's a whole lot of reasons why Mach was slow,
但是很多人看到这些基准测试结果，
but many people saw those benchmark results,
显示 Mach 比原始操作系统慢得多，
showing that Mach was much slower than native operating systems
并认为微内核是无可救药的低效的，
and decided that micro kernels were just hopeless, hopelessly inefficient,
不太可能快到可以竞争，
where unlikely ever to be fast enough to be competitive
我们都应该使用宏内核。
and you know we should just all use monolithic kernels.
今天的论文就像是对这一论点的回答，
Today's papers like an answer basically to that argument,
在某种程度上是对这一论点的反驳，
it's sort of the rebuttal to that argument,
这篇论文的重点是展示
and the point of this paper is to show
你可以构建这个架构，
that you can build this architecture,
如果你注意优化性能，
and if you pay attention to optimizing performance,
你可以得到有竞争力的性能，
you can get a competitive performance
与直接运行 Unix 的原生操作系统相比，
with native operating systems just directly running Unix,
所以，你不能简单地根据性能来排除微内核，
and therefore you can't dismiss micro kernels simply on the basis of performance,
你可能因为其他原因不想要它们，
you may not want them for other reasons,
但你不能以性能作为拒绝的理由，
but you can't use performance as the reason to reject,
提出这一论点的很大一部分原因是，
part of, a huge part of the ingredients in making that argument is that,
他们使用我几分钟前提到的技术使 IPC 变得更快，
they made the IPC much faster with the techniques that I outlined a few minutes ago
你可以看到这一点，我认为在一个非常简单的基准表 2 中，
and you can see this I think in a, in a very simple benchmark table 2,
如果你有论文的复制，
if you have a copy of the paper with you,
表 2 是在硬件上以普通方式运行的原生 Linux 的测量结果，
table 2 as measurements of just native Linux running in the ordinary way on hardware
在原生 Linux 上，他们展示了
and on native Linux, they show that
他们的硬件和 Linux 版本，
you know on their hardware and their version of Linux,
一个个简单的系统调用 getpid 花费了 1.7 微秒，
that a single simple system call getpid took 1.7 microseconds,
它们还表明，
and they also show that
在 L4 设置相同的东西，
the sort of equivalent thing in there L4 setup,
你必须发送 IPC 请求并获得 IPC 响应，
where you have to send an IPC request and get an IPC response
仅针对 getpid 系统调用，
just for this getpid system call,
在 L4 Linux 下，这需要 4 微秒的时间，
that that that took four microseconds under L4 Linux,
这意味着两倍的时间，
which is to say twice as long,
但是有两倍的工作在进行，
but there's twice as much work going on,
因为你进行两组用户内核穿越，
because you're doing two sets of user kernel crossings
不只是一个简单的系统调用，
instead of just a single simple system call,
也就是说，他们可以声称，
that is they could claim
他们让这些 IPC 基础系统调用的花费降到了最低，
that they appeared the expense of these IPC base system calls down to basically the minimum,
这是系统调用原生 Linux 花费的两倍，
that is twice the cost of system call native Linux
所以，他们的表现几乎和你预期的一样好。
and therefore they were doing roughly as good as you could possibly expect.
当然，现在他们的系统速度仍然只有原生 Linux 的一半，
Now, of course that's still their systems are still half as fast as native Linux,
这不是很清楚，
and you know it's not clear
除非你做一些测量，系统调用是否运行了两次，
unless you did some measurements whether system calls taking twice
或者简单的系统调用花费两倍的时间是灾难还是不是问题。
or simple system calls taking twice as long as a disaster or not a problem.
为了表明这一点，
And in order to show that,
这可能是一场灾难，如果你执行大量系统调用，
you know it might be a disaster, if you do a lot of system calls
或者可能不成问题，如果你执行的系统调用相对较少，
or might be not a problem, if you do relatively few system calls
或者每个系统调用有很多工作，
or there's a lot of work per system calls,
可能系统调用比 getpid 更复杂。
maybe a system calls are more complicated than getpid.
论文中的答案是 A 图基准测试，
And the answer to that in the paper is the figure A benchmark,
使用这个名为 AIM 的基准测试，
using this benchmark called AIM,
这只是一个，
which is just a more,
它是一个各种不同的系统调用的基准测试，
it's a benchmark that has all kinds of different system calls,
它读写文件，创建进程，
it reads and writes files and creates processes
用内核做进程做的所有事情，
does all the things with the kernel that processes do,
他们在图 A 中显示，
and they basically showed in figure A that
他们的设置运行的是一个更完整的应用程序，
their setup running a much more full application that does,
不仅仅是 getpid ，
much more than just getpid,
运行速度仅比本地 Linux 慢几个百分点，
runs only a few percent slower than native Linux,
所以，你可以预期，
and therefore, hopefully you could expect
无论你想在计算机上运行什么，
that whatever it is you wanted to run on a computer,
在 L4 上运行几乎与 Linux 同样快，
would run almost as fast under L4 as Linux,
就像在普通操作系统下一样，
as it does under a straight operating system,
在原生操作系统下，
under native operating system
所以，它们
and therefore you know they were basically
基本上和直接运行 Linux 一样快，
to a first approximation as fast as just running straight Linux
所以，你应该认真对待它们。
and therefore you should take them seriously.
好的，这是一个令人印象深刻的结果，
Okay, so that was an impressive result by the way,
这是一个出乎意料的，并且很酷，
this is like someone unexpected and cool,
快进 20 年后，这一切就结束了，
just fast forwarding twenty years, where this ended up,
正如我之前提到的，
as I mentioned before,
人们在很多嵌入式环境中使用 L4 ，
people actually use L4 in a bunch of embedded situations,
特别是它用得很多，
particularly its used a lot,
智能手机上运行 L4 的例子很多，
there are many instances of L4 running in in smartphones,
隐藏在人们的视线之外，但不管怎样，
hidden from view but nevertheless,
并且所有运行的各种自定义软件，
and all running various kinds of custom software,
在这种情况下，它们不必与 Unix 兼容，
not not running, they don't have to have compatibility with Unix, in these situations,
微内核在其他更一般的情况下，
micro kernels in other more general situations
如工作站或服务器中从未真正流行起来，
like workstations or servers never really caught on,
这并不是因为这个设计一定有什么问题，
and it's not because there's necessarily anything wrong with that design,
只是为了取代一些现有的软件，
it's just they would have in order to displace some existing software,
你的新东西必须是更好的，
your new thing has to be you know like better,
让人们将会被激励去转换。
so people will be motivated to switch.
这些微内核是很好的，自然优雅，
And these micro kernels were perfectly good, naturally elegant,
但是人们很难确切指出
but it was hard to put, for people to put their finger on,
为什么它要好得多，
why it was so much better,
他们应该不厌其烦地
that they should go to the trouble
从 Linux 或他们正在运行的切换过来，
of switching from Linux or whatever they were running fits,
所以它从来没有真正流行起来，
so it never really caught on,
不一定是出于很好的原因，
not necessarily for good reasons,
因为它们看起来要好得多。
but because they were like dramatically better.
另一方面，
On the other hand,
来自这个架构的许多想法都产生了持久的影响，
many ideas from this architecture had a lasting impact,
人们得出，
the the people have to work out
更多有趣和灵活的方式来使用虚拟内存，
much more interesting and flexible ways of using virtual memory
为了在微内核上支持操作系统，
in order to support operating systems on their micro kernels
这些更复杂的接口
and those more sophisticated interfaces
通过 mmap 等方式进入 Linux 等主流操作系统，
made their way through things like mmap into mainstream operating systems like Linux,
这种在顶层运行操作系统的想法，
this idea of running an operating system kind of on top,
作为低级操作系统之上的服务器，
as a as a server on top of a lower level operating system,
在今天以虚拟机监视器的形式非常流行，
is extremely popular today in the form of virtual machine monitors,
它们在各地使用各种云托管服务。
which use all over the place and sort of cloud hosting services.
对可扩展性的需求，你可以修改用户级服务，
The desire for extensibility, you could modify a user level service,
在 Linux 中发挥作用的方式是可加载的内核模块，
the way that played out in things like Linux was loadable kernel modules
允许你动态加载修改 Linux 内核的工作方式，
which allow you to load, modify the way the Linux kernel works on the fly,
当然还有客户端服务器的类型，
and of course the sort of client server,
对客户端服务器体系结构的良好支持，
good support for this client server architecture,
也进入了像 MacOS 这样的内核，
also made its way into kernels like MacOS,
它具有良好的 IPC 和良好的客户端服务器。
which has good IPC and good client server.
这就是我对这堂课要说的全部内容，
And that's all I have to say for this lecture,
我很乐意留下来回答问题，谢谢。
I'm happy to stick around for questions, thank you.
谢谢。
Thank you.
不用谢。
You're welcome.
哦，我想问一下，
Oh, I wanted to ask,
我们现在讨论的论文关于页表，
so the paper we're talking about virtual, about page tables,
我想是在 4.2 ，
at I think 4.2
它说的是如何，
and it was saying how,
我想这和你之前提到的差不多，
I think it was kind of what what you mentioned before,
你说有一种错误的方式可以做到这一点，
where you said that there is a wrong way to do that,
我想可能有点类似，
I think might be kind of similar to that,
但是如果做这件事，
but if you do this, this thing
你现在在照片里解释的这件事，
that you explain this in your picture now,
在这种情况下，页表是如何工作的？
would it be, I guess how how would the page tables work in this case?
好的，你可能指的是 4.3 节，双空间错误。
Well, are you, you may be referring to section 4.3 the dual space mistake.
哦，是的，抱歉， 4.3 。
Oh yes sorry 4.3.
是的，这是一个有点复杂的故事，
Yeah, that's a bit of a complicated story,
但让我们看看，
but the let's see,
背景的一部分是 Linux 在那些日子里的工作方式，
part of the background is the way that Linux worked in those days,
事实上，直到最近，都是
and indeed until recently is that
当你在用户级别运行时，
the when you're running at user level,
页表实际上有，
the page table, this actually has
进程页面，用户级页映射，
both the processe's pages, user level pages mapped in
并且所有内核都映射到这个页表中，
and all of the kernel mapped into that one page table,
在 x86 上，
on xv6 anyway,
所以，当你进行系统调用并跳入内核时，
so when you made system call, and jumped into the kernel,
内核已映射到页表中，
the kernel was already mapped into the page table
因此不需要页表切换，
and therefore no page table switch was required,
当你进行系统调用时，
when you make a system call,
它的成本要低得多，
its that much more expensive and much more cheaper,
因为没有页表切换，
because there was no page table switch,
如果你在 xv6 中调用，
if you're call in xv6,
你知道 trampoline 代码切换页表，
you know the trampoline code switches page tables,
这是一件昂贵的事情，
which is an expensive thing to do,
因为它刷新虚拟到物理映射的 TLB 高速缓存。
because it flushs the TLB cache of virtual to physical mappings.
无论如何，为了提高效率，
Anyway, so for efficiency,
Linux 在同一页表中映射内核和用户空间，
Linux used to map kernel and user space in the same page table
具有很快的系统调用，
had fast system calls as a result,
原因并不是很清楚，
so they for reasons that aren't very clear,
他们决定执行相同的操作来设置 Unix 服务器中的映射。
decided to do this same thing to setup the mapping in the Unix server.
好的，他们想要的是，
Well, what they wanted was that
当 VI ，当一个进程将系统调用发送到这里时，
when VI, when a process send a system call over here,
他们希望页表处于活动状态，
they wanted to have the page table that was active,
在 Linux 服务器上处理那个系统调用的时候，
well, in the Linux server while processing that system call,
包括所有虚拟内存映射，
include all the virtual memory mappings,
send 系统调用的进程的映射。
mappings for the process that sent the system call.
这至少使它，
And that at least would make it
更容易的查找传给系统调用参数的虚拟地址，
simpler to look up virtual addresses past a system call arguments,
比如发送给 read ，
like pass to read,
之所以效果不佳，
the reason why this worked out poorly,
原因有很多，
there are a bunch of reasons,
一是 L4 对 Linux 的东西一无所知，
one is that, L4 which doesn't know anything about any of Linux stuff,
L4 只知道有两个进程，
L4 just knows there's two processes
所以，当你将 IPC 从一个进程发送到另一个进程时，
and so when you send an IPC from one process to another,
L4 只是切换页表，
L4 just switches page tables,
它总是只切换页表，
it always just switches page tables,
这个页表， VI 的页表，
this guy the page table, VI, the page table,
L4 将页表与 Linux 内核相关联，
L4 associates a page table with Linux kernel,
只是总是切换页表，
just always switches page tables,
所以，你甚至不能，
so you couldn't even
由于 L4 系统调用的实现方式不同，
due the L4 due to the different way system calls are implemented
并且涉及 L4 的事实是，
and the fact that L4 was involved,
在系统调用期间没有办法保留页表，
there was no way to preserve the page table during a system call,
那是不可能的，
that just wasn't possible,
因为 L4 总是切换页表，
because L4 always switched page tables
当它在从一个进程切换到另一个进程时，
when it switched from one process to another,
所以，他们永远不会获得无需切换页表的效率优势，
so they were never going to get the efficiency win of not having to switch page tables,
当它一旦从用户到内核的切换时。
when that once a crossing from from user to kernel.
但我认为他们想要方便
But I think they wanted the convenience
能够直接使用用户提供的虚拟地址，
of being able to directly use user supplied virtual addresses,
但这意味着映射是活跃的，
but that meant that mappings they needed to be active
取决于它们代表哪个进程执行系统调用，
depended on which process they were executing a system call on behalf of,
所以 Linux 不可能有任何一个页表，
so there couldn't be any one page table for Linux,
LINUX 页表是否使用取决于发送系统调用 RPC 的进程，
page table Linux sort of one is used depends on what process sent system call RPC,
但是 L4 不知道怎么玩这个游戏，
but L4 did not know how to play that game,
L4 将单个页表与每个进程与每个任务相关联，
L4 associated a single page table with each process with each task,
所以它只会切换到那个页表，
and so in order and it would just switch to that page table,
所以运气不好，
so tough luck,
Linux 没有任何方法使页表不同，
Linux didn't have any way to cause the page table to differ
根据 send 系统调用的不同，
depending on who it's sent to the system call,
为了解决这个问题，
in order to deal with that,
他们制作了一堆内核的共享内存副本，
apparently they made a bunch of shared memory copies of the kernel,
每个进程一个，
one for each process
所以每个内核的共享内存副本，
and so each of these shared memory copies of the kernel,
将所有内核内存映射到其中，
had exact had all of the kernel memory mapped into it,
所以它们都是相同的内核数据结构，
so they were all the same kernel data structures,
但是每个进程都有一个与之相关联的专用内核任务，
but each process had a dedicated kernel task associated with it
所以，这允许他们对 L4 使用技巧，
and therefore that basically allowed them to trick L4
并切换到适当的页表，
and to switch into the appropriate page table,
包括进程加上内核，
that included that process plus the kernel,
具体取决于哪个进程系统调用请求。
depending on which process system call request.
我觉得那挺管用的，
And you know I think that kind of worked,
但是他们说他们工作很慢之类的，
but I don't [] what they said they worked was slow or something,
因为有很多任务。
because there were a lot of tasks.
不管怎么说，这是个复杂的故事，
Anyway, it's a complicated story,
我认为这件事的效果不是很好。
and I think it didn't work out very well for this.
好的，我明白了，
Okay, okay I see,
我想这很好地解释了为什么这个东西更难，
I think I think that explains well why this thing is harder to do
比我们做的 xv6 ，好的。
than, well, what we do xv6, okay.
是的，这个，因为没有，
Yeah yeah, this, because there's not,
你有这张图片 xv6 甚至标准的 Linux
you have this picture xv6 or even standard Linux
都比这个简单得多，
is much simpler than this,
你只是直接跳到内核中，
you're just jumping directly into the kernel
并且内核对所有分页硬件有直接控制权，
and the kernel has control over direct control over all the paging hardware,
当它运行 L4 时就没有了。
which doesn't have when it runs L4.
好的，我明白了，谢谢。
Right, okay I see, thank you, thank you.
我们会问，为什么，
We're gonna ask, why,
看起来有些任务比其他任务更适合放在内核之外，
it seems like some some tasks are more appropriate to be put outside the kernel than others,
但是这个 L4 使用微内核的方法，
but this L4 like the approach with micro kernels
似乎总是要么什么都有，要么什么都不是，
always seems to be either everything or nothing,
比如要么有一个宏内核来做所有的事情，要么什么都不做，
like either you have a monolithic kernel doing everything or nothing,
比如我觉得分页和其他一些事情在内核中可能非常有效，
just like I feel like paging and some other things could be very efficient inside the kernel,
然后可能像文件系统，
and then maybe like file systems
需要交换的东西可能在外部，
that things that need to be swappable could be outside,
然后，甚至可以拥有一个具有某些功能的内核，
and then even like you can maybe even have a kernel that has some functionality,
但是你可以选择不使用它，而提供你自己的，
but you can opt to not use it and provide your own,
有没有什么。
is there any thing.
你说的绝对是对的，
You say is absolutely well taken
确实有很多微内核或与微内核相关的项目，
and indeed there were a lot of micro kernel or micro kernel related projects
它们中的许多制造了各种各样的混合内核，
and many of them built various kinds of hybrids,
比如有几个不同版本的 Mach ，
like there's actually a couple different versions of Mach
其中一些是混合内核，
and some of them sort of hybrid kernels,
有这样一个微内核 IPC ，
which yeah there was this micro kernel that knew about IPC,
但内核中是一个完整的 Unix ，
but also in the kernel was a complete Unix,
比如， Mach 2.5 就是在内部使用混合内核，
so for instance Mach 2.5 was this hybrid with it,
微内核和 Unix 几乎都在同一个内核中。
but micro kernel and Unix all sort of in the same kernel
你可以进行系统调用，
and you can make system calls either
而且一些东西使用了微内核的方式，
and some stuff was built in the sort of micro kernel way,
但是有些东西他们只是用了 Mach 的内核，
but some things they were just used the kernel that was in Mach,
它在 Mach 内核中，
that was built into the Mach kernel,
Unix 内核被内置到 Mach 内核中，
the Unix kernel was built into the Mach kernel,
一种现代 MacOS 构建方式也与所描述的方式类似，
a modern MacOS also built in a way that like the way you describe,
MacOS 有一个完整的操作系统，
you know MacOS has a complete operating system
里面有一个文件系统和所有的东西，
with a file system and everything inside it,
但它也很好地支持 IPC 和类似的线程，
but it also has good support for IPC and sort of like threads,
所有你想要构建的微内核式服务。
all the stuff you would want to build micro kernel style services.
谷歌的 Fuchsia 是不是也实现了其中一些想法？
Is Google's Fuchsia, I'm aware of also implements some of these ideas as well.
我敢打赌是的。
I'll bet yeah.
所以不管怎样，没有一种方法，
So anyway, there's no one way,
有些人希望一个纯粹的，
there were people who were sort of hoping that a pure,
非常纯粹的计划能够奏效，
a very pure scheme could be made to work,
这不是唯一可能的前进道路。
it's not the only possible way forward.
好的，谢谢，
Alright, thanks,
我要去我的下一节课了，
got around my next lecture,
但是我们会再见的。
but I'll see you guys.
再见。
See you later.
谢谢。
Thank you.
不用谢。
You're welcome.
哦，我没有，
Oh, I I didn't have a,
我只想说一句，
I have just a remark,
我觉得很有意思，
I I think it's fascinating,
它好像慢了 5% ，
that it it's like 5% slower,
但它做的工作要多得多，
but it does so much more work,
是的，它非常有意思。
yeah was fascinated with that.
你的意思是，即使它做更多的工作也只是稍微慢一点，
You mean that even though it's doing much more work is only slightly slower,
IPC 的性能真的是[]。
really have a really [] over the IPC performance.
当然，还有一件事需要记住，
And it's another thing to remember, of course is that,
如果你开始做，
if you start doing,
如果你在每个系统调用中做大量的工作，
if you're doing a significant amount of work per system call,
查找文件和目录什么的，
you know looking at files and directories or something,
那么系统调用的成本，
then the cost of the system call,
IPC 本身成本就开始变得不那么重要了。
the IPC itself starts to be less important.
所以，更快的系统调用加上实际程序的组合
So the combination of faster system calls plus real programs
可以做一些不同于进行系统调用的事情。
do things other than making system calls.
但你也会希望交换页表。
But you would also like switch page tables and.
是的。
Yeah.
其他系统有的。
The others have.
是的，尽管论文，
Yeah, although the paper,
我没有谈到它，
I did not talk about it,
但是论文有一些巧妙的技巧，
but the paper had some clever tricks
可以避免切换页表的成本，
for avoiding the cost of switching page tables,
我不知道你是否还记得，
I don't know if you remember for some of its,
在第 6 页中，我们讨论的是标记 TLB 为很小的空间，
on page 6, we're talking about supporting tagged TLBs a small spaces,
他们有一些聪明的想法来避免切换页表，
they have some clever ideas for not switch page tables,
这是我在读这份论文之前听说过的。
which I had not heard of before I read this paper.
太酷了，非常感谢，再见。
This is pretty cool, thank you so much, bye.
再见。
Goodbye.